<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015-2018  D. Brian Walton     -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="accumulation-rates">
  <title>Rate of Accumulation and the Derivative</title>

  <subsection>
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <p>
    We have learned that functions defined as accumulation functions,
    <men xml:id="eqn-accumulation-function-with-rate">f(x) = f_0 + \int_{x_0}^x f'(z) \, dz</men>,
    can be described in terms of monotonicity and concavity in terms of
    the signs and monotonicity of the rate of accumulation <m>f'(x)</m>.
    Of course, most functions are not written with an accumulation formula representation.
    This raises a central question of calculus: 
    Which functions <em>can</em> be expressed as an accumulation?
    And if a function can be expressed as an accumulation, 
    how do we find the formula for the rate of accumulation 
    that will be the integrand in that representation?
    </p>
    
    <p>
    At present, we have formulas relating the rate of accumulation and the accumulation function
    only for simple polynomials. (See <xref ref="thm-elementary-accumulation-functions"/>.)
    In this section, we will discuss how to use those elementary accumulation rates and functions
    to compute the rate of accumulation for simple polynomials. 
    We will also illustrate some additional examples of describing 
    the monotonicity and concavity of a function in terms the corresponding rate function.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    Looking forward, we will need new tools to find the rate function for more complicated functions.
    To do this, we will be introducing a new concept called the instantaneous rate of change
    or derivative at a point. This notion of a derivative is defined in terms of a limit.
    The properties of limits will allow us to develop properties of derivatives.
    These properties will allow us to create differentiation rules to compute derivative functions
    that will characterize the instantaneous rate of change of a function at any point
    where the derivative is defined.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    At that stage of development, 
    we will have two notions of rate of change<mdash/>the rate of accumulation and the derivative.
    These are, in fact, the same thing, which we will establish as the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.
    Because the rate of accumulation and derivative are different interpretations of the same thing,
    we will use the language of derivatives now even though in context, we are thinking
    in terms of the integrand of an accumulation function.
    </p>
  </subsection>
   
  <subsection>
    <title>The Rate of Accumulation</title>
    
    <p>
    When a function is defined as an accumulation function <xref ref="eqn-accumulation-function-with-rate">in terms of a definite integral</xref>,
    it is easy enough to determine the rate of accumulation or derivative by identifying the function in the integrand.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        If <m>f(x)</m> is defined as <m>\displaystyle f(x) = 3 + \int_1^{x} z^2-5z \, dz</m>, 
        then the integrand <m>z^2-5z</m> must be <m>f'(z)</m>. 
        Changing variables means <m>f'(x) = x^2-5x</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </example>
    
    <p>
    The linearity properties of definite integrals imply that rates of accumulation also satisfy linearity properties.
    Thus, we can think of polynomials as sums of elementary components whose derivatives are known.
    </p>
    
    <theorem xml:id="thm-linearity-of-accumulation-rates">
      <title>Linearity of Rates of Accumulation</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        If <m>f(x)</m> has a rate of accumulation <m>f'(x)</m> and <m>g(x)</m> has a rate of accumulation <m>g'(x)</m>,
        then the function <m>h(x)=c_1 f(x) + c_2 g(x)</m> with constants <m>c_1</m> and <m>c_2</m> has 
        a rate of accumulation <m>h'(x) = c_1 f'(x) + c_2 g'(x)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <proof>
        <p>
        Using a common initial point at <m>x=a</m>, we can write
        <md>
          <mrow>f(x) = f(a) + \int_a^x f'(z) \, dz,</mrow>
          <mrow>g(x) = g(a) + \int_a^x g'(z) \, dz.</mrow>
        </md>
        Because <m>h(x) = c_1 f(x) + c_2 g(x)</m>, we can use the linearity properties of definite integrals to rewrite
        <md>
          <mrow>h(x) &amp;= c_1 \Big(f(a) + \int_a^x f'(z) \, dz\Big) + c_2 \Big(g(a) + \int_a^x g'(z) \, dz\Big)</mrow>
          <mrow>&amp;= c_1 f(a) + c_2 g(a) + c_1 \int_a^x f'(z) \, dz + c_2 \int_a^x g'(z) \, dz</mrow>
          <mrow>&amp;= (c_1 f(a) + c_2 g(a)) + \int_a^x (c_1 f'(z) + c_2 g'(z)) \, dz</mrow>
        </md>
        Since <m>h(a) = c_1 f(a) + c_2 g(a)</m>, we can see that <m>h(x)</m> has been written in the form of an accumulation
        with a rate of accumulation <m>h'(x) = c_1 f'(x) + c_2 g'(x)</m>.
        </p>
      </proof>
    </theorem>
    
    <p>
    The <xref ref="thm-elementary-accumulation-functions">elementary accumulation formulas for simple powers</xref>
    can be interpreted as complementary rules to find the rate of accumulation for simple powers. 
    As an example, consider the known accumulation formula
    <me>\int_0^x z^2 \, dz = \frac{1}{3}x^3.</me>
    If we multiply both sides of the equation by <m>3</m> to clear the fraction and move the constant inside the integral,
    we have an equivalent statement
    <me> x^3 = \int_0^x 3z^2 \, dz.</me>
    That is, we have just found that if <m>f(x)=x^3</m> then <m>f'(x)=3x^2</m>.
    Each accumulation formula allows us to identify a corresponding rate of accumulation for simple powers.
    </p>

    <theorem xml:id="thm-accumulation-rate-simple-powers">
      <title>The Power Rule for the Rate of Accumulation</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        The elementary accumulation formulas lead to the following elementary rates of accumulation for powers of the independent variable.
        <ul>
          <li><p>If <m>f(x) = x</m>, then <m>f'(x)=1</m>.</p></li>
          <li><p>If <m>f(x) = x^2</m>, then <m>f'(x)=2x</m>.</p></li>
          <li><p>If <m>f(x) = x^3</m>, then <m>f'(x)=3x^2</m>.</p></li>
          <li><p>If <m>f(x) = x^4</m>, then <m>f'(x)=4x^3</m>.</p></li>
        </ul>
        </p>
      </statement>
      <proof>
        <p>
        Each formula follows by applying the same technique described above for <m>f(x)=x^3</m> on the corresponding accumulation formula.
        </p>
      </proof>
    </theorem>

    <p>
    You might have noticed a pattern in these formulas, that the rate of accumulation involves a power that has been reduced by one
    from the accumulation function and that the power for the accumulation has become a constant multiple.
    Without creating more accumulation formulas, we can not prove that this pattern will always be true.
    In mathematics, we call a pattern that we believe might be true a <term>conjecture</term>.
    </p>
    
    <conjecture xml:id="conjecture-accumulation-rate-power-rule">
      <title>Power Rule for Rate of Accumulation</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        For any constant power <m>n</m>, 
        the function <m>f(x) = x^n</m> has a rate of accumulation <m>f'(x) = n x^{n-1}</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </conjecture>
    
    <p>
    This conjecture happens to be true, but we will need to wait to develop the process of differentiation to prove it.
    We will need one more simple rate of accumulation to deal with constant terms.
    A constant function sees no change, so the accumulation must always be zero, and that will come from a rate of accumulation that is zero.
    </p>
    
    <theorem xml:id="thm-accumulation-rate-for-constant">
      <title>Rate of Accumulation for Constants</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        If <m>f(x) = c</m> for some constant <m>c</m> (a constant function), then <m>f'(x)=0</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <proof>
        <p>
        Because <m>\displaystyle \int_a^b 0 \, dx = 0</m>, we can write <m>\displaystyle f(x) = c + \int_{a}^{x} 0 \, dz</m> for any value <m>a</m>.
        Thus, the rate of accumulation <m>f'(x) = 0</m>.
        </p>
      </proof>
    </theorem>

    <p>
    With these building blocks now in place and the linearity properties available to put them together,
    we are ready to find the rate of accumulation (the derivative) for simple polynomials.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Find <m>f'(x)</m> for <m>f(x) = x^2 - 6x + 5</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        We look at <m>f(x)</m> as a sum of three terms: <m>f_1(x)=x^2</m>, <m>f_2(x)=-6x</m>, and <m>f_3(x)=5</m>.
        First, <m>f_1(x)=x^2</m> is an elementary power for which we know <m>f_1'(x)=2x</m>.
        Next, <m>f_2(x)=-6x</m> is a constant <m>-6</m> times <m>x</m>, so <m>f_2'(x)</m> is the same constant times <m>1</m>, <m>f_2'(x)=-6\cdot 1 = -6</m>.
        Finally, <m>f_3(x)=5</m> is a constant function so that <m>f_3'(x)=0</m>.
        The linearity for rates of accumulation implies <m>f'(x)=2x-6+0 = 2x-6</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <title>Using the Rate of Accumulation</title>
    
    <p>
    Now that we know how to find the rate of accumulation for simple polynomials,
    we can express a polynomial as an accumulation with that rate.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>Express <m>f(x)=x^3 - 6x^2 - 4</m> as an accumulation from <m>x=1</m>.</p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        Start by finding the rate of accumulation.
        <me>f'(x)=3x^2 - 6(2x) + 0 = 3x^2 - 12x</me>
        The rate of accumulation becomes the integrand of the accumulation.
        Because the integral will start at <m>x=1</m>, the initial value will be
        <me>f(1) = 1^3 - 6 \cdot 1^2 - 4 = -9.</me>
        We can now write <m>f(x)</m> as an accumulation from <m>x=1</m>:
        <md>
          <mrow>f(x) &amp;= f(1) + \int_1^x f'(z) \, dz</mrow>
          <mrow>&amp;= -9 + \int_1^x 3z^2 - 12z \, dz.</mrow>
        </md>
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
    
    <p>
    The sign of the rate of accumulation determines whether an accumulation is increasing or decreasing.
    Furthermore, the monotonicity of the rate of accumulation determines the concavity of the accumulation.
    If we determine the rate of accumulation for a polynomial <m>f(x)</m>, then we can use sign analysis
    on the resulting formula <m>f'(x)</m> to characterize monotonicity of <m>f(x)</m>.
    Because the rate of accumulation <m>f'(x)</m> will itself be a new polynomial, we can describe its monotonicity
    using the rate of accumulation for that rate of accumulation. 
    This is called the <term>second derivative</term> and is named <m>f''(x)</m>.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        We found that <m>f(x)=x^3-6x^2-4</m> has corresponding rate <m>f'(x)=3x^2-12x</m>.
        Describe the monotonicity and concavity of <m>f(x)</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        Sign analysis of the rate of accumulation <m>f'(x)</m> will be used to describe the monotonicity of <m>f(x)</m>.
        We factor <me>f'(x)=3x^2-12x=3x(x-4).</me>
        The zeros (<m>x</m>-intercepts) occur at <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=4</m> and <m>f'(x)</m> is continuous.
        We need to test the sign of <m>f'(x)</m> in the intervals <m>(-\infty,0)</m>, <m>(0,4)</m>, and <m>(4,\infty)</m>.
        Only the sign matters, so using the factored formula, we can count how many factors are positive and negative.
        <ul>
          <li><m>f'(-1)=3(-1)(-5) = +</m> (2 negative factors)</li>
          <li><m>f'(1)=3(1)(-3) = -</m> (1 negative factors)</li>
          <li><m>f'(5)=3(5)(1) = +</m> (0 negative factors)</li>
        </ul>
        When doing such a problem, we just use a sign analysis number line to record our results.
        </p>
        
        <sidebyside margins="auto">
          <image width="70%">
            <latex-image-code>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}[x=0.5cm,y=1cm]
            \draw[<->] (-4,0) -- (8,0)
              node[pos=1, above right] {$f'(x)=3x(x-4)$}
              node[pos=1, below right] {$x$};
            \draw (0, -0.1) -- (0,0.1) 
              node[pos=0, below] {$0$}
              node[pos=1, above] {$0$};
            \draw (4, -0.1) -- (4,0.1)
              node[pos=0, below] {$4$}
              node[pos=1, above] {$0$};
            \node [above] at (-1,0.1) {$+$};
            \node [above] at (1,0.1) {$-$};
            \node [above] at (5,0.1) {$+$};
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
        
        <p>
        We interpret the signs of <m>f'(x)</m> to deduce the monotonicity of <m>f(x)</m>.
        The function <m>f'(x)</m> is positive on the intervals <m>(-\infty,0)</m> and <m>(4,\infty)</m>
        and negative on the interval <m>(0,4)</m>.
        Consequently, <m>f(x)</m> must be increasing on the intervals <m>(-\infty,0)</m> and <m>(4,\infty)</m>
        and decreasing on the interval <m>(0,4)</m>.
        Because <m>f(x)</m> is continuous (all polynomials are continuous), we can extend each of these intervals
        to include the end-points at <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=4</m>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Concavity of <m>f(x)</m> depends on the monotonicity of <m>f'(x)</m>.
        Because <m>f'(x)=3x^2-12x</m> is itself a polynomial, we can find its rate of accumulation <m>f''(x)</m>
        and perform sign analysis to deduce that monotonicity.
        <me>f''(x) = 6x-12=6(x-2)</me>
        The only zero of <m>f''(x)</m> is at <m>x=2</m>.
        We test the intervals <m>(-\infty,2)</m> and <m>(2,\infty)</m> using the signs of <m>f''(x)</m>,
        summarized by the following number line.
        </p>
        
        <sidebyside margins="auto">
          <image width="70%">
            <latex-image-code>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}[x=0.5cm,y=1cm]
            \draw[<->] (-4,0) -- (8,0)
              node[pos=1, above right] {$f''(x)=6(x-2)$}
              node[pos=1, below right] {$x$};
            \draw (2, -0.1) -- (2,0.1) 
              node[pos=0, below] {$2$}
              node[pos=1, above] {$0$};
            \node [above] at (-1,0.1) {$-$};
            \node [above] at (5,0.1) {$+$};
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
        
        <p>
        Because <m>f''(x) \lt 0</m> on the interval <m>(-\infty,2)</m>, 
        we know that <m>f'(x)</m> is decreasing on <m>(-\infty,2)</m>.
        Consequently, <m>f(x)</m> is concave down on  <m>(-\infty,2)</m>.
        Because <m>f''(x) \gt 0</m> on the interval <m>(2,\infty)</m>, 
        we know that <m>f'(x)</m> is increasing on <m>(2,\infty)</m>.
        Consequently, <m>f(x)</m> is concave up on  <m>(2,\infty)</m>.
        Again, because <m>f(x)</m> is continuous, intervals of concavity can be extended to include the end-point at <m>x=2</m>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Notice how the graph of <m>y=f(x)</m> reflects the monotonicity and concavity that we have determined.
        </p>
        
        <figure margins="auto">
          <caption>Graph of <m>y=f(x)=x^3-6x^2-4</m>, including turning points at <m>x=0</m> and <m>x=4</m>
          and an inflection point at <m>x=2</m>.</caption>
          <image width="70%">
            <latex-image-code>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}
            \begin{axis}
              [
                xmin=-3, xmax=7, ymin=-50, ymax=15,
                axis lines=center,
              ]
            \addplot [samples=100, domain=-2.5:6.5] {x^3-6*x^2-4};
            \addplot [samples at={0,2,4}, only marks] {x^3-6*x^2-4};
            \end{axis}
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </figure>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
    <ul>
      <li>
      </li>
    </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <exercises>
  </exercises>
</section>