<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->

<section xml:id="differentiation-related-rates">
  <title>Differentiation and Related Rates</title>
  <introduction>
    <p>
      We often fall into a trap thinking that the rules of differentiation apply only to formulas.
      Some times, two or more quantities are added together to form a new quantity representing their sum.
      Other times, a quantity of interest is determined by multiplying the values of two measurements.
      The rules of differentiation apply to any setting
      where we are interested in how the rate of change a quantity
      relates to the rates of change of quantities with which it is related.
      If we know the instantaneous values and rates of change of these quantities,
      we can find the instantaneous rate of change of the new variable
      even when we do not know any formulas for our underlying variables.
    </p>
    <p>
      In this section, we consider examples of using related rates of change
      to find the instantaneous rate of change of a quantity that depends on other related variabes.
      In each example, we will first recognize how related dependent variables are algebraically combined.
      Then we can use rules of differentiation to identify a new equation that relates their rates of change.
      This equation, in turn, allows us to solve for the unknown rate.
    </p>
  </introduction>
  <subsection>
    <title>A Physical Example of the Sum Rule</title>
    <p>
      The <xref ref="sum-rule-deriv" text="title">sum rule for derivatives</xref> tells us
      that the derivative of a sum of two functions equals the sum of the individual derivatives.
      In the context of rates of change, this means that when a dependent variable is equal to the sum of two other dependent variables,
      then the rate of change of the new variable must equal the sum of the rates of change of the dependent variables being added.
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A tank is being filled with water two supply hoses.
          At a particular instant, if the first hose is pumping water at a rate of 20 gal/min
          and the second hose is pumping water at a rate of 30 gal/min,
          at what rate is volume of water in the tank changing?
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          We know the intuitive solution to the problem is 50 gal/min.
          This is actually a consequence of the sum rule of derivatives.
          We can think of the water in the tank as having two components:
          <m>W_1</m>, the volume of water (gal) that was pumped by hose 1,
          and <m>W_2</m>, the volume of water (gal) that was pumped by hose 2.
          These two variables are functions of time <m>t</m> (min),
          although we do not know any formulas for these functions (and don't need to).
        </p>
        <p>
          The rates of water flowing from the hoses correspond to derivatives:
          <me>\frac{dW_1}{dt} = 20, \quad \frac{dW_2}{dt} = 30.</me>
          The total volume of water in the tank at a given time <m>t</m> is the sum
          <m>W(t)=W_1(t) + W_2(t)</m>.
          By the sum rule of derivatives,
          <me>\frac{dW}{dt} = \frac{dW_1}{dt} + \frac{dW_2}{dt} = 20+30 = 50. </me>
          Technically, we should have a constant added to <m>W</m>
          that represents the initial amount of water in the tank and didn't come from either hose.
          Because the derivative of a constant is zero, this will not change the result.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>A Physical Example of the Product Rule</title>
    <p>
      The sum rule for derivatives feels very intuitive. If a quantity is the sum
      of parts, then the total rate of change for the quantity is the sum of the
      rates of change for each of the parts. The product rule is less intuitive
      because we don't get to multiply rates of change when a quantity is a product.
      To illustrate this example, we focus on a geometric example on the area of a
      rectangle when the lengths of the sides are changing.
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A city is in the shape of a rectangle with sides aligned with North-South and East-West
          lines. Suppose that the city is currently 5 miles east-to-west and 3 miles north-to-south
          and plans to expand to a size 8 miles east-to-west by 5 miles north-to-south over the
          next 10 years. What is the average rate of change of the total area in the city
          over the 10 years? If the borders were to move at a constant rate over those 10 years,
          what is the instantaneous rate of change of the total area of the city at the
          beginning and at the end of the 10 years?
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          The average rate of change of total area is calculated according to the usual formula.
          It does not follow the differentiation rules, which are about instantaneous rates of change.
          We let <m>A</m> represent the area of the city and <m>t</m> the time in years from now.
          The city currently has a total area of
          <me>A(0) = 5 \times 3 = 15 \: \hbox{mi}^2</me>.
          After 10 years, the city will have a total area of
          <me>A(10) = 8 \times 5 = 40 \: \hbox{mi}^2</me>.
          The change in area is <m>\Delta A = A(10)-A(0) = 25 \: \hbox{mi}^2</m>
          and the change in time is <m>\Delta t = 10</m> years.
          Consequently, the average rate of change of area is
          <me>\frac{\Delta A}{\Delta t} \Big|_{0,10} = \frac{25}{10} = 2.5\: \hbox{mi}^2/\hbox{yr}</m>.
        </p>
        <sidebyside>
          <image>
            <latex-image>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}
            \draw[fill,red!25] (0,0) rectangle (4,2.5);
            \draw[fill,blue!25] (0,0) rectangle (2.5,1.5);
            \draw[<->] (0,-0.15) -- (2.5,-0.15) node [pos=0.5,below] {$W(0)=5$};
            \draw[<->] (0,-0.75) -- (4,-0.75) node [pos=0.5,below] {$W(10)=8$};
            \draw[<->] (-0.15,0) -- (-0.15,1.5) node [pos=0.5, left] {$H(0)=3$};
            \draw[<->] (4.15,0) -- (4.15,2.5) node [pos=0.5, right] {$H(10)=5$};
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
        <p>
          To connect our intuition with functions and to prepare for the
          next calculations, let us introduce variables in addition to time <m>t</m> and total area <m>A</m>.
          The state of the city can be characterized more precisely with two more variables:
          the distance east-to-west, which we'll call the width <m>W</m> (mi),
          and the distance north-to-south, which we'll call the height <m>H</m> (mi).
          We think of <m>W</m>, <m>H</m> and <m>A</m> as being dependent variables
          as they are each a function of time <m>t</m>.
          They are related variables because the area always equals the product of <m>W</m> and <m>H</m>:
          <me> A(t) = W(t) \cdot H(t).</me>
        </p>
        <p>
          To find the instantaneous rates of change,
          we need to know how fast the width and height measurements are changing in time.
          Because the problem stated that these changed at a constant rate,
          we can use the average rates of change to compute the instantaneous rates:
          <md>
            <mrow>\displaystyle \frac{dW}{dt} = \left. \frac{\Delta W}{\Delta t}\right|_{[0,10]}
            = \frac{W(10)-W(0)}{10-0} = \frac{8-5}{10} = 0.3, </mrow>
            <mrow>\displaystyle \frac{dH}{dt} = \left. \frac{\Delta H}{\Delta t}\right|_{[0,10]}
            = \frac{H(10)-H(0)}{10-0} = \frac{5-3}{10} = 0.2. </mrow>
          </md>
          Since the area <m>A</m> is the product of <m>W</m> and <m>H</m>,
          the product rule for derivatives will provide the instantaneous rate of change for area:
          <me>\frac{dA}{dt} = \frac{d}{dt}[W \cdot H] = \frac{dW}{dt} \cdot H + W \cdot \frac{dH}{dt}. </me>
          This equation is the related rates equation.
        </p>
        <p>
          When <m>t=0</m> we have <m>W(0)=5</m> and <m>H(0)=3</m> so that
          <md>
            <mrow> \left. \frac{dA}{dt} \right|_{0}
            &amp;= \left.\frac{dW}{dt}\right|_{0} \cdot H(0) + W(0) \cdot \left.\frac{dH}{dt}\right|_{0}</mrow>
            <mrow> &amp;= 0.3(3) + 5(0.2) = 1.9.</mrow>
          </md>
          That is, at the beginning, the city is expanding at a rate of <m>1.9 \: \hbox{mi}^2/\hbox{yr}</m>.
          After 10 years, <m>t=10</m>, we have <m>W(10)=8</m> and <m>H(10)=5</m> so that
          <md>
            <mrow> \left. \frac{dA}{dt} \right|_{10}
            &amp;= \left.\frac{dW}{dt}\right|_{10} \cdot H(10) + W(10) \cdot \left.\frac{dH}{dt}\right|_{10}</mrow>
            <mrow> &amp;= 0.3(5) + 8(0.2) = 3.1.</mrow>
          </md>
          At the end of the 10 years, the city is expanding at a rate of <m>3.1 \: \hbox{mi}^2/\hbox{yr}</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
          The picture of expanding area helps provide some intuition for why the product rule
          is the appropriate technique. If we consider the city after 6 months (<m>t=0.5</m>),
          both the width and the height have changed by a small amount, as shown in the figure
          below. The total change in area has two primary contributions, corresponding to
          long, skinny rectangles with areas <m>W(0) \cdot \Delta H</m> and <m>\Delta W \cdot H(0)</m>,
          and a very small rectangle with area <m>\Delta W \cdot \Delta H</m>. The product
          rule corresponds to the rate of change coming from the two primary contributions
          while the small rectangle leads to a term that has a limit of zero in the calculation
          of the derivative.
        </p>
        <sidebyside>
          <image>
            <latex-image>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}
            \draw[fill,red!25] (0,0) rectangle (5.15,3.1);
            \draw[black, thick] (0,0) rectangle (5.15,3.1);
            \draw[fill,blue!25] (0,0) rectangle (5,3);
            \draw[black, thick] (0,0) rectangle (5,3);
            \draw (5,3.1) -- (5,3) -- (5.15,3);
            \draw[<->] (0,-0.15) -- (5,-0.15) node [pos=0.5,below] {$W(0)=5$};
            \draw[<->] (-0.15,0) -- (-0.15,3) node [pos=0.5, left] {$H(0)=3$};
            \draw[<-] (-0.05, 3.05) -- (-0.5, 3) node[left] {$\Delta H$};
            \draw[<-] (5.075, -0.05) -- (5.15,-0.5) node[below] {$\Delta W$};
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>A Physical Example of the Quotient Rule</title>
    <p>
      Quotients often appear when working with densities, concentrations, or other ratios.
    </p>
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
          A salt-water solution is being formulated. At a particular instant,
          the solution consists of 10 L of water with 5 kg of salt.
          At that instant, water is being added at a rate of 0.5 L/s
          while salt is being added at a rate of 0.2 kg/s.
          What is the instantaneous rate of change of the concentration?
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
          We start by identifying the variables that define the state of our system.
          The variables include the time <m>t</m>, measured in seconds (s),
          the total volume of water <m>V</m>, measured in liters (L),
          the total amount of salt in the water <m>S</m>, measured in kilograms (kg),
          and the concentration of salt water <m>C</m>, measured in kilograms per liter (kg/L).
          The variables <m>V</m>, <m>S</m> and <m>C</m> are functions of time <m>t</m>
          with an equation relating them by
          <me>C(t) = \frac{S(t)}{V(t)} \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad C = \frac{S}{V}.</me>
        </p>
        <p>
          The instantaneous rate of change is computed using the quotient rule for derivatives,
          giving us a related rates equation
          <me> \frac{dC}{dt} = \frac{ V \frac{dS}{dt} - S \frac{dV}{dt}}{V^2}. </me>
          The values at the instant in question are given by
          <md>
            <mrow> V = 10, \quad \frac{dV}{dt} = 0.5, </mrow>
            <mrow> S = 5, \quad \frac{dS}{dt} = 0.2. </mrow>
          </md>
          Using these values in the quotient rule for derivatives, we have
          <me> \frac{dC}{dt} = \frac{ 10(0.2) - 5(0.5) }{10^2} = \frac{2-2.5}{100} = -0.005. </me>
          That is, the concentration is changing at a rate of -0.005 kg salt per liter water per second.
          Alternatively, we could say that the concentration is decreasing at a rate of 0.005 kg/L/s.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>

</section>
