<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->

<section xml:id="differentiable-functions">
    <title>Differentiable Functions</title>

    <subsection>
      <p>Placeholder: Remember to address differentiability of rational powers somewhere.</p>
    </subsection>
    <subsection>
        <title>Consequences of Differentiability</title>

        <p>There are a number of important consequences of a function being differentiable. These consequences are stated as mathematical theorems that you will need to know by name. We begin by introducing terminology about local extreme values.</p>

        <definition xml:id='defn-local-extremes'>
            <title>Local Maximum and Minimum</title>
            <statement>
                <p>A function <m>f</m> has a <term>local maximum</term> at a point <m>x=a</m> if <m>f(a) \ge f(x)</m> for all <m>x</m> in a neighborhood of <m>a</m>. It has a <term>local minimum</term> at <m>x=a</m> if <m>f(a) \le f(x)</m> for all <m>x</m> in a neighborhood of <m>a</m>.</p>
            </statement>
        </definition>

        <p>The first theorem is about the slope at a local extreme. It guarantees that a local extreme can only occur where the function either is not differentiable or has a horizontal tangent line.</p>

        <theorem xml:id='fermats-theorem'>
            <title>Fermat's Theorem</title>
            <statement>
                <p>If <m>f</m> has a local extreme at <m>x=a</m> and <m>f'(a)</m> exists, then <m>f'(a)=0</m>.</p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>

        <p>The second theorem combines the <xref ref='extreme-value-theorem' text='title'>Extreme Value Theorem</xref> with Fermat's Theorem. If a function is continuous on a closed interval <m>[a,b]</m>, then it must achieve both a maximum and a minimum value. If that function has <m>f(a)=f(b)</m>, then one of the extreme values must occur inside the interval at some point <m>c \in (a,b)</m>. If the function is also differentiable, then we must have <m>f'(c)=0</m>. This result is named Rolle's theorem.</p>

        <theorem xml:id='rolles-theorem'>
            <title>Rolle's Theorem</title>
            <statement>
                <p>If <m>f</m> is continuous on <m>[a,b]</m> and differentiable on <m>(a,b)</m> and <m>f(a)=f(b)</m>, then there must be some value <m>c \in (a,b)</m> so that <m>f'(c)=0</m>.</p>
            </statement>
        </theorem>

        <p>The consequence of Rolle's theorem is that if a function starts and ends at the same value over an interval, it must turn around somewhere. For a differentiable function, the slope at that point must be <m>f'(c)=0</m>.</p>

        <p>The third theorem about differentiability applies Rolle's theorem to say something about the average rate of change. Recall that the <xref ref='defn-average-rate-of-change' text='title'>average rate of change</xref>, <me>\left.\frac{\Delta f}{\Delta x}\right|_{[a,b]} = \frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a},</me> is the slope of the line, called a <term>secant line</term>, that joins the points <m>(a,f(a))</m> and <m>(b,f(b))</m>. The Mean Value Theorem guarantees that a continuous and differentiable function will have some point at which the tangent line has the same slope as the secant line over the interval.</p>

        <theorem xml:id='mean-value-theorem'>
            <title>Mean Value Theorem</title>
            <statement>
                <p>If <m>f</m> is continuous on <m>[a,b]</m> and differentiable on <m>(a,b)</m>, then there must be some value <m>c \in (a,b)</m> so that <me>f'(c)=\frac{f(b)-f(a)}{b-a}.</me> Alternatively, we sometimes rewrite this as <me>f(b)-f(a)=f'(c) \cdot (b-a).</me></p>
            </statement>
            <proof>
                <p>Let <m>s(x)</m> be the linear function corresponding to this secant line and then define <m>g(x)=f(x)-s(x)</m>. Since <m>s(a)=f(a)</m> and <m>s(b)=f(b)</m>, we have <m>g(a)=g(b)=0</m>. If <m>f</m> is continuous and differentiable, then so is <m>g</m>. Rolle's theorem guarantees that <m>g'(c)=f'(c)-s'(c) = 0</m> for some value <m>c \in (a,b)</m>. Thus, <m>f'(c)=\left.\frac{\Delta f}{\Delta x}\right|_{[a,b]}</m>.</p>
            </proof>
        </theorem>

    </subsection>
</section>
