<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--
The frontmatter contains a variety of items that precede
the actual content.  They tend to get placed in the "right"
place and order, and not necessarily the order they appear here.
They differ from "docinfo" items in that they will be *content*
that a reader will actually see.

The xml:id string is used to form a filename for the webpage.
Setting this one to "index" makes for a good default page
when you host your project on a server.
-->

<frontmatter xml:id="index">
  <!--
  Items typically on the main title page, perhaps duplicated
  in the half-title page, page headings, etc.
  One exception - main title and (optional) subtitle follow
  the scheme for titling any division of the work.
   -->

  <titlepage>

     <!-- There can be several authors here -->
    <author>
      <personname>D. Brian Walton</personname>
      <department>Department of Mathematics and Statistics</department>
      <!-- Use "break" tag anywhere for forced line break -->
      <institution>
        <line>James Madison University</line>
        <line>Harrisonburg, Virginia, USA</line>
      </institution>
      <email>waltondb@jmu.edu</email>
    </author>

    <!-- Can set date manually or use the "today" element -->
    <date><today /></date>

  </titlepage>

  <!--
  Acknowledgements, dedications, colophon (ISBN, copyright, etc)
  are supported in the book document type.  Such a diverse range
  is not yet available for articles.  Send requests.
  -->
   
  <preface xml:id="preface">
    <p>
    Calculus is a branch of mathematics that studies functions
    through the processes of limits, derivatives, and integrals.
    This text introduces the ideas of calculus through the context
    of mathematical models.
    This text is organized to review precalculus concepts
    necessary to be successful in learning calculus.
    The goal is not, however, to introduce these concepts
    to a beginner but to leverage some familiarity toward a deeper understanding.
    </p>
    <p>
    The text begins with a basic review of numbers and variables
    with an aim of connecting these foundational concepts 
    to the goals of modeling relationships between physically measured quantities.
    It then turns to the development of functions as the mathematical
    tool used for predictive relationships between variables.
    Intuitive ideas of continuity are introduced in relationship 
    to making piecewise functions connected, with limits introduced as a way
    to characterize the behavior of a function at the break points.
    </p>
    <p>
    Sequences are introduced early as a discrete illustration
    of many of the concepts relating to modeling with functions.
    Patterns found in sequences are familiar to students
    and these patterns can often be described both explicitly and recursively.
    This will serve as a prelude to the idea that functions can be
    defined explicitly with a formula or indirectly through differential equations.
    In addition, sequences foreshadow the ideas of limits, derivatives, and integrals.
    Describing the monotonicity and concavity of a sequence
    then provides a direct correspondence to describing the behavior
    of a function in terms of its first and second derivatives.
    </p>
    <p>
    Summation rules and formulas naturally occur as part of the discussion of sequences.
    This motivates an early introduction of the definite integral
    as the generalization of the accumulation of increments of change.
    The rate of change is introduced in the context of accumulation
    and the reader is explicitly told to look forward to the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus
    as the formal connection between the rate of accumulation and the instantaneous
    rate of change as being equivalent.
    Properties of the definite integral as well as elementary formulas are introduced.
    The behavior of functions in terms of the first and second derivative are
    introduced using the integral representation of functions.
    </p>
    <p>
    Next, we develop a more thorough investigation of limits and continuity of functions.
    Properties of limits are developed in the context of the limits of sequences.
    The epsilon-delta definition of a limit is given in an optional section.
    Continuity of functions is formalized and the major theorems for continuous functions
    are presented, namely the Intermediate Value Theorem and the Extreme Value Theorem.
    </p>
    <p>
    This is followed by the formal development of the derivative and the rules of differentiation,
    including the first part of the Fundamental Theorem of Calculus.
    Applications of derivatives and antiderivatives are included.
    </p>
    <p>
    You can download a PDF copy of the book with the links below. 
    There are differently formatted options, depending on how you intend to use the PDF.
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <p><url href="http://educ.jmu.edu/~waltondb/MA2C/model-calculus.pdf">http://educ.jmu.edu/~waltondb/MA2C/model-calculus.pdf</url> (Margins formatted to print 2-sided)</p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p><url href="http://educ.jmu.edu/~waltondb/MA2C/model-calculus-1page.pdf">http://educ.jmu.edu/~waltondb/MA2C/model-calculus-1page.pdf</url> (Margins formatted to print 1-sided)</p>
        </li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>
    In order to keep track of changes during the semester, 
    the following list describes the changes that have taken 
    place in the text since August 2017.</p>
    
    <ul>
        <li></li>
    </ul>
  </preface>
</frontmatter>
