<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="functions-introduction">
    <title>An Introduction to Functions</title>

    <subsection>
        <title>Overview</title>
        
        <p>Calculus studies the relationships between variables. These relationships are most often expressed in terms of functions. In mathematics, a function is the a predictive relationship between an independent and a dependent variable such that knowing the value of the independent variable allows us to predict the value of the dependent variable.</p>
        
        <p>In this section, we will review concepts relating to functions that are taught in algebra and pre-calculus. We start with linear relations. Linear functions will motivate many of the ideas throughout this course.</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <!-- Functions -->
    <subsection>
        <title>Linear Functions</title>
        
        <p>A <term>linear relation</term> is a relation between two variables, say <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>, such that the graph of all states <m>(x,y)</m> is a geometric line. Every line in the <m>(x,y)</m> plane can be characterized by an equation of the form <men xml:id="general-eqn-line">Ax+By=C,</men> where <m>A</m>, <m>B</m> and <m>C</m> are constants. Equation <xref ref="general-eqn-line"/> is called the <term>general equation of a line</term>.</p>
        <p>Horizontal and vertical lines are special cases. A <term>horizontal line</term> occurs when the <m>y</m>-values of every state are the same. The equation of a horizontal line is of the form <m>y=C</m>. A <term>vertical line</term> occurs when the <m>x</m>-values of every state are the same. The equation of a vertical line is of the form <m>x=C</m>.</p>
        <note>
            <statement>
                <p>In mathematics, <term>definitions</term> provide the precise meaning of words that describe mathematical objects. Mathematics is a <term>deductive</term> science, meaning that mathematical truth is determined by showing that definitions are satisfied using logical reasoning. For example, we can think of the general equation of a line in Equation <xref ref="general-eqn-line"/> as the definition of a line. We can reason that what we have described as horizontal and vertical lines are actually lines. For example, the equation <m>y=C</m> satisfies the general equation of a line with <m>a=0</m> and <m>b=1</m>. The logical argument used to show a definition is satisfied is called a <term>proof</term>.</p>
            </statement>
        </note>
        <p>We say that an equation defines <m>y</m> as a function of <m>x</m> if we can solve the equation for <m>y</m>. That is, we can write the equation in an equivalent form where <m>y</m> equals an expression that only involves <m>x</m>. This includes the possibility that <m>y</m> equals a constant. This new equation with <m>y</m> isolated defines <m>y</m> as <term>an explicit function</term> of <m>x</m>.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement><p>Show that the line <m>2x+3y=6</m> defines <m>y</m> as a function of <m>x</m> by writing <m>y</m> as an explicit function of <m>x</m>.</p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p>We start with the equation <m>2x+3y=6</m> and solve the equation for <m>y</m>. <md>
                    <mrow>2x+3y=6</mrow>
                    <mrow>3y=-2x+6</mrow>
                    <mrow>y=\frac{-2x+6}{3}</mrow>
                    <mrow>y=-{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2</mrow>
                </md> The equation <m>y=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m> defines <m>y</m> as an explicit function of <m>x</m>.</p>
            </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>There is nothing particularly special about solving for <m>y</m>. We might instead solve for <m>x</m>. The variable that we isolate is called the <term>dependent variable</term> and the other variable is called the <term>independent variable</term>.</p>

        <example>
            <statement><p>Show that the line <m>2x+3y=6</m> also defines <m>x</m> as a function of <m>y</m>.</p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p>Starting with the equation <m>2x+3y=6</m>, we isolate <m>x</m>. <md>
                    <mrow>2x+3y=6</mrow>
                    <mrow>2x=-3y+6</mrow>
                    <mrow>x=\frac{-3y+6}{2}</mrow>
                    <mrow>x=-{\textstyle \frac{3}{2}}y+3</mrow>
                </md> The equation <m>x=-\frac{3}{2}x+3</m> defines <m>x</m> as an explicit function of <m>y</m>. In this context, <m>x</m> is the dependent variable and <m>y</m> is the independent variable.</p>
            </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>When an equation in two variables defines each variable as a function of the other, as illustrated in the previous examples, the two functions are called <term>inverse functions</term>. We say that the relation is <term>one-to-one</term> because each value of either variable uniquely identifies a single value of the other variable.</p>
        
        <p>An explicit function provides a convenient way to predict the value of the dependent variable knowing the value of the independent variable. We substitute the given value of the independent variable into the equation, compute the value of the explicit expression, and that value is the predicted value of the dependent variable. If we were to use the original equation, we could also substitute the value of the independent variable but then we would need to solve for the unknown dependent variable. The explicit function has the advantage that the solving process was already performed.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement><p>For the line <m>2x+3y=6</m>, find the value of <m>y</m> when <m>x=2</m>.</p></statement>
            <solution>
                <p>If we use the original equation, we can substitute the value of <m>x=2</m> into the equation <m>2x+3y=6</m> and solve for <m>y</m>. <md>
                    <mrow>2x+3y=6</mrow>
                    <mrow>2(2)+3y=6</mrow>
                    <mrow>4+3y=6</mrow>
                    <mrow>3y=2</mrow>
                    <mrow>y={\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}</mrow>
                </md></p>
                <p>On the other hand, we earlier solved for <m>y</m> as an explicit function <me>y=-\frac{3}{2}x+3.</me> Substituting <m>x=2</m> into this equation directly gives us the desired value. <md>
                    <mrow>y&amp;=-{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2</mrow>
                    <mrow>y&amp;=-{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}(2)+2 =-{\textstyle \frac{4}{3}}+{\textstyle \frac{6}{3}}={\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}</mrow>
                </md></p>
            </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>To wrap-up this quick overview of linear function, we should talk about slope. This subsection started with the general equation of a linear relation <m>Ax+By=C</m>. What if we start with data instead of the equation? How do we find an appropriate equation? A linear relation is characterized by having a constant slope. Knowing the slope and one state (or point), we can find an equation of the line.</p>
        
        <definition xml:id="definition-slope">
            <title>Slope of a Linear Relation</title>
            <statement>
                <p>For every linear relation with states <m>(x,y)</m>, there is a constant value, say <m>m</m>, such that for any two states <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)</m>, <me>m = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1}.</me> The value <m>m</m> is called the <term>slope</term>. For a vertical line, since all <m>x</m>-values are the same and <m>x_2-x_1=0</m>, the slope is undefined.</p>
            </statement>
        </definition>
        
        <p>One of the most well-remembered equation from algebra is the <term>slope<ndash/>intercept equation of a line</term>, <me>y=mx+b,</me> which is the equation of a line with slope <m>m</m> and with a <m>y</m>-intercept at the state <m>(x,y)=(0,b)</m>. If we know any other state, since <m>b=y-mx</m>, we can find the value of the intercept using the values of the known point.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement>
                <p>For each of the following data tables, determine if the data could come from a linear relation. If so, give an equation of the line. <ol>
                    <li><tabular>
                    <col right="major"/> <col right="minor"/> <col right="minor"/> <col/>
                    <row bottom="major">
                        <cell><m>x</m></cell> <cell>1</cell> <cell>4</cell> <cell>10</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><m>y</m></cell> <cell>5</cell> <cell>3</cell> <cell>-1</cell>
                    </row>
                    </tabular></li>
                    <li><tabular>
                    <col right="major"/> <col right="minor"/> <col right="minor"/> <col/>
                    <row bottom="major">
                        <cell><m>x</m></cell> <cell>2</cell> <cell>6</cell> <cell>12</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell><m>y</m></cell> <cell>11</cell> <cell>19</cell> <cell>27</cell>
                    </row>
                    </tabular></li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        <p>For the first data set, we measure the slope if we compare the first point with each of the other two points. If those are the same, then the data are consistent with a linear relation. Let us label the states <m>(x_1,y_1)=(1,5)</m>, <m>(x_2,y_2)=(4,3)</m>, and <m>(x_3,y_3)=(10,-1)</m>. Compute the slopes: <md>
                            <mrow> \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1} &amp;= \frac{3-5}{4-1} = -\frac{2}{3} </mrow>
                            <mrow> \frac{y_3-y_1}{x_3-x_1} &amp;= \frac{-1-5}{10-1} = -\frac{6}{9} = -\frac{2}{3} </mrow>
                        </md> Because the slopes are the same value <m>m=-\frac{2}{3}</m>, there is a linear relation with these states.</p>
                        <p>We find the equation <m>y=mx+b</m> by computing <m>b=y-mx</m> using one of the given states and <m>m=-\frac{2}{3}</m>, such as <m>(x_1,y_1)=(1,5)</m>: <me>\textstyle b = 5-(-\frac{2}{3})(1) = 5+\frac{2}{3} = \frac{17}{3}.</me> The linear relation is characterized by the equation <me>\textstyle y=-\frac{2}{3}x+\frac{17}{3}.</me> If we multiply both sides by 3, we can find an equivalent equation involving only integers <m>3y = -2x+17</m>, which is equivalent to an equation <m>2x+3y=17</m>.</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>For the second data set, we measure the slopes using the states <m>(x_1,y_1)=(2,11)</m>, <m>(x_2,y_2)=(6,19)</m>, and <m>(x_3,y_3)=(12,27)</m>: <md>
                            <mrow> \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1} &amp;= \frac{19-11}{6-2} = \frac{8}{4} = 2 </mrow>
                            <mrow> \frac{y_3-y_1}{x_3-x_1} &amp;= \frac{27-11}{12-2} = \frac{16}{10} = \frac{8}{5} </mrow>
                        </md> Because the slopes have different values, these data are not consistent with a linear relation.</p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </solution>
        </example>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
        <title>Function Notation</title>

        <p>When a function will be used repeatedly, the function is assigned a name, which might be a letter, a word, or any symbol. In math textbooks, the most common name is <m>f</m>. We write <m>x \overset{f}{\mapsto} y</m> as a symbolic statement that <m>f</m> is the function relating an independent variable <m>x</m> and a dependent variable <m>y</m>. We call this notation using an arrow <term> function mapping notation</term>. The arrow summarizes that the function lets us use values of <m>x</m> to predict the value of <m>y</m>. If we have an explicit function, we can use use the equation on the right hand side or just the expression if the name of the dependent variable is not required.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement>
                <p>The explicit function <m>y=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m> assigned to a function with name <m>f</m> would be written using function mapping notation as <me>x \overset{f}{\mapsto} y=-{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2,</me> or, if we didn't need the name of the dependent variable, as <me>x \overset{f}{\mapsto} -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2.</me> The inverse function <m>x=-\frac{3}{2}y+3</m> would need a different name, say <m>g</m>. We would write <me> y \overset{g}{\mapsto} x=-{\textstyle \frac{3}{2}}y+3.</me></p>
            </statement>
        </example>
        
        <p>Using substitution of the independent variable for a named function is made simpler using <term>function evaluation notation</term>. This is done by writing the function name followed by a value or an expression enclosed in parentheses. Whatever is inside of the parentheses is the value substituted in place of the independent variable.</p>
        
        <note xml:id="function-notation-not-multiplication">
            <statement>
                <p>Although writing parentheses in mathematics next to a number or a variable means multiplication, a function is not a variable. The parentheses after the function do <em>not</em> mean multiplication but evaluation. It is unfortunate that the same symbols have different meanings, so you will need to pay close attention to the context.</p>
            </statement>
        </note>
        
        <p>Function evaluation notation can be used in place of function mapping notation to define a function.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement>
                <p>The statement <m>f(x)=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m> and <m>x \overset{f}{\mapsto} -\frac{2}{3}x+2</m> are exactly equivalent. If we wish to name the dependent variable, we would need to say <m>y=f(x)=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m>. The evaluation notation is interpreted as <q>the output value of the function <m>f</m> with independent variable <m>x</m> is <m>-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m>.</q> It is usually read more concisely as saying <q>the value of <m>f</m> of <m>x</m> is <m>-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m>.</q></p>
            </statement>
        </example>
        
        <p>The next few examples illustrate how evaluation notation relates to substitution.</p>
        
        <example>
            <statement>
                <p>For <m>f(x)=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m>, simplify each of the following expressions. <ol>
                    <li><m>f(4)</m></li>
                    <li><m>f(t)</m></li>
                    <li><m>f(3x+1)</m></li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        <p>To simplify <m>f(4)</m>, we see that the value inside parentheses is 4. So we substitute the independent variable with the value 4. <md>
                            <mrow>f(x) &amp;= -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2</mrow>
                            <mrow>f(4) &amp;= -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}(4)+2 = {-\textstyle \frac{8}{3} + \frac{6}{3}} = {\textstyle -\frac{2}{3}}</mrow>
                        </md></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>The expression <m>f(t)</m> substitutes the variable <m>t</m> in place of <m>x</m>: <me>f(t) = -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}t+2.</me></p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>The expression <m>f(3x+1)</m> substitutes the expression <m>3x+1</m> for the independent variable <m>x</m>. Although the original independent variable of <m>f(x)=-\frac{2}{3}x+2</m> is <m>x</m>, we should think of this substitution in terms of a placeholder <m>f(\square)=-\frac{2}{3}\square+2</m> and substitution <m>\square = 3x+1</m>. <md>
                            <mrow>f(x) &amp;= -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}x+2</mrow>
                            <mrow>f(\square) &amp;= -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}\square+2</mrow>
                            <mrow>f(3x+1) &amp;= -{\textstyle \frac{2}{3}}(3x+1)+2</mrow>
                            <mrow> &amp;= \textstyle -\frac{2}{3}(3x) + -\frac{2}{3}(1) + 2 </mrow>
                            <mrow> &amp;= \textstyle -2x + \frac{4}{3}</mrow>
                        </md> Introducing the placeholder symbol <m>\square</m> is not necessary but might help emphasize that we are not including things with the <m>x</m> but performing an actual substitution, <m>\square = 3x+1</m>.</p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </solution>
        </example>
        
        <note>
            <statement>
                <p>When an expression is inside the parentheses of function evaluation notation, you should use parentheses at the substitution step as well to ensure that the entire expression is being used. Once substitution occurs, you should then be sure to apply standard algebraic rules appropriately.</p>
            </statement>
        </note>
        
        <example>
            <statement>
                <p>For <m>g(y)=-\frac{3}{2}y+3</m>, simplify each of the following expressions. <ol>
                    <li><m>g(x)</m></li>
                    <li><m>g(2t)</m></li>
                    <li><m>3g(2x)+1</m></li>
                </ol></p>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <ol>
                    <li>To find <m>g(x)</m> requires a simple substitution. <md>
                        <mrow>g(y) &amp;= \textstyle -\frac{3}{2}y+3</mrow>
                        <mrow>g(x) &amp;= \textstyle -\frac{3}{2}x+3</mrow>
                    </md></li>
                    <li>To find <m>g(2t)</m> requires a substitution of the expression <m>x=2t</m>. <md>
                        <mrow>g(2t) &amp;= \textstyle -\frac{3}{2}(2t)+3</mrow>
                        <mrow> &amp;= -3t+3</mrow>
                    </md></li>
                    <li>To find <m>3g(2x)+1</m> will require substitution of <m>g(2x)</m> by a formula that itself involves substitution. Note the use of parentheses. <md>
                        <mrow>3g(2x)+1 &amp;= 3\Big({\textstyle  -\frac{3}{2}(2x)+3}\Big) + 1</mrow>
                        <mrow> &amp;= 3(-3x+3)+1 = -9x+9+1</mrow>
                        <mrow> &amp;=-9x+10</mrow>
                    </md></li>
                </ol>
            </solution>
        </example>
    </subsection>
    
</section>