<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="linear-models">
	<title>Linear Models</title>

	<!-- Linear Equations -->
	<subsection>
		<title>Linear Equations</title>
		<p>
		A linear relation between two variables, say <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>,
		is when the <em>change</em> between the variables, rather than the variables themselves,
		are proportional.
		</p>
		
		<definition>
			<title>Linear Relation</title>

			<statement>
				<p>
				Given two covarying variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>, we say that <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>
				have a <term>linear relation</term> if there exist some constants <m>A</m>, <m>B</m> and <m>C</m>
				such that for every state of the system, the variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> satisfy
				<me>Ax+By=C.</me>
				The graph of such a relation in the Cartesian plane is a line.
				</p>
			</statement>
		</definition>
		
		<p>
		The form of the equation used in the definition of a linear relation is called the
		general equation for a line. This equation can describe horizontal, vertical and slanted lines.
		A vertical line occurs in the <m>x</m>-<m>y</m> plane when the value of <m>x</m> is
		the same regardless of the value of <m>y</m>, or <m>x</m> is independent of <m>y</m>.
		This corresponds in the general equation with <m>B=0</m> and the equation can be rewritten
		as <m>x=a</m> with <m>a=C/A</m>, where <m>a</m> represents the constant value of <m>x</m> over
		all states of the system.
		</p>
		
		<p>
		With the exception of the case of that <m>x</m> is constant (discussed above), for linear relations
		we say that <m>y</m> is a linear function of <m>x</m>.
		</p>
		
		<definition>
			<title>Linear Function</title>

			<statement>
				<p>
				Given two covarying variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m>, we say that <m>y</m> 
				is a <term>linear function</term> of <m>x</m> if there exist a constant <m>m</m>
				such that for any two states of the system <m>(x_1,y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2,y_2)</m>,
				the ratio of the change in <m>y</m>, <m>\Delta y = y_2-y_1</m>,
				to the change in <m>x</m>, <m>\Delta x = x_2-x_1</m>, always equals <m>m</m>,
				<me>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1} = m.</me>
				</p>
				<p>
				That is, the change in <m>y</m> is proportional to the change in <m>x</m>,
				or <m>\Delta y \propto \Delta x</m>.
				The ratio of the changes, or <term>rate of change</term>, is called the <term>slope</term>.
				</p>
			</statement>
		</definition>
		
		<p>
		Many students finish algebra courses remembering the <term>slope<ndash/>intercept form</term>
		of the equation of a line, 
		<me> y = mx+b, </me>
		and have unfortunately used it so much that they think this is a preferred form.
		This equation's form involves two model parameters, the slope <m>m</m> and 
		the <m>y</m><ndash />intercept, <m>b</m>. An <term>intercept</term> describes a point
		where a graph crosses one of the axes in the plane. A <term><m>y</m>-intercept</term>
		is a point where the graph crosses the <m>y</m>-axis. So this form of the line requires
		knowing the slope <m>m</m> and the value of <m>y</m> when <m>x=0</m> so that <m>(x,y)=(0,b)</m>
		is a known state.
		</p>
		<notation>
			<title>Slope<ndash />Intercept Form of Linear Function</title>
			<usage>y=mx+b</usage>
			<description>Equation of a line with slope <m>m</m> passing through the <m>y</m>-axis at <m>(x,y)=(0,b)</m>.</description>
		</notation>
		
		<p>
		It would be much better to remember the more general <term>point<ndash/>slope form</term>,
		<me> y-y_1 = m(x-x_1). </me>
		Although this form involves three parameters, it is structured in a way that reminds
		you of the definition of the slope and the idea of proportional change,
		<me>\Delta y = m \cdot \Delta x.</me>
		In addition to the slope <m>m</m>, we need one particular known point for the state
		<m>(x,y) = (x_1,y_1)</m>.
		If we solve for <m>y</m>, this form is written
		<me> y = y_1 + m(x-x_1), </me>
		which mathematically says that the value of <m>y</m> for a corresponding value of <m>x</m>
		is equal to the known value of <m>y=y_1</m> at some known value <m>x=x_1</m> plus the
		change that is proportional to <m>\Delta x=x-x_1</m>.
		</p>
		<notation>
			<title>Point<ndash />Slope Form of Linear Function</title>
			<usage>y=y_1+m(x-x_1)</usage>
			<description>Equation of a line with slope <m>m</m> passing through a point <m>(x,y)=(x_1,y_1)</m>.</description>
		</notation>

		<p>
		If you remember the point<ndash />slope form of an equation for a line, other uses can
		be immediately recovered.
		For example, if you do know the <m>y</m><ndash/>intercept <m>b</m>, 
		then you know a point <m>(x,y)=(0,b)</m>.
		The resulting point<ndash />slope form becomes equivalent to the slope<ndash/>intercept form,
		<me>y=b+m(x-0) = b+mx.</me>
		But if you instead know the <m>x</m><ndash/>intercept <m>a</m>, then you know
		a point on the <m>x</m><ndash/>axis <m>(x,y)=(a,0)</m> and the point<ndash />slope form 
		immediately leads to an equation capturing this information,
		<me>y=m(x-a).</me>
		</p>
		
		<example>
		    <statement>
		    Write <m>y</m> as a linear function of <m>x</m> if we know that <m>y=24</m>
		    when <m>x=5</m> and the rate of change is <m>\frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x}=-3</m>.
		    </statement>
		    <solution>
                <p>
		        This is an ideal setting to use the point<ndash />slope form 
		        because we know the slope <m>m=-3</m> and we know a point <m>(x,y)=(5,24)</m>.
		        One way to do this is to write down the slope equation using <m>(x,y)</m>
		        and <m>(5,24)</m> to get
		        <me> \frac{y-24}{x-5} = -3. </me>
		        After cross-multiplying and solving for <m>y</m>, we get
		        <me> y = -3(x-5) + 24. </me>
		        </p>
		        
		        <p>
		        The other way to do this problem is to start with the general formula
		        <me> y = m(x-a) + b </me>
		        where <m>m</m> is the slope and <m>(a,b)</m> is a known point.
		        Since we know <m>m=-3</m> and our point is <m>(a,b)=(5,24)</m>,
		        we can use these values as our model parameters to get
		        <me> y = -3(x-5) + 24. </me>
                </p>
		    </solution>
		</example>
		
		<p>
		If we have two points, we need to calculate the slope before proceeding.
		One special application of this is the idea of <term>linear interpolation</term>.
		Often, we have data for two variables where we expect there is a nice relation
		between the variables but we do not know an appropriate formula.
		Linear interpolation adopts a modeling strategy that between any two neighboring
		data points, a linear model should give a reasonable approximation.
		So the strategy involves identifying which two points to use, finding the
		appropriate slope and equation of a line, and then use the equation to
		approximate the unknown point.
		</p>

        <example>
            <statement>
            <p>
            The following graph illustrates data representing the volume of water
            in a draining container <m>V</m> (liters) at various times <m>t</m> (seconds).
            Approximate how much water was in the container after 35 seconds.
            </p>
            <sidebyside>
                <image>
                    <description>
                    Data points at (0, 6.4), (20, 4.8), (40, 3.6), (60, 2.7).
                    </description>
                    <latex-image>
                    <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                    <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                    }
                    \begin{tikzpicture}
                    \begin{axis}[
                        xmin=-10,xmax=70,ymin=0,ymax=8,
                        xtick={
                            0, 20, 40, 60
                            },
                        ytick={0, 2, 4, 6, 8},
                        xlabel={$t$ (seconds)},
                        ylabel={$V$ (liters)},
                    ]

                    \addplot[red, only marks] table {
                        0 6.4
                        20 4.8
                        40 3.6
                        60 2.7
                    }
                    node [pos=0,above] {(0, 6.4)}
                    node [pos=0.33, above] {(20, 4.8)}
                    node [pos=0.67, above] {(40, 3.6)}
                    node [pos=1, above] {(60, 2.7)};
                    \end{axis}
                    \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                    </latex-image>
                </image>
            </sidebyside>
            </statement>
            <solution>
                <p>
                The data are given at times <m>t \in \{0, 20, 40, 60\}</m>. 
                Notice that although the change in time is always <m>\Delta t = 20</m>
                for consecutive points, the change in volume for consecutive points
                is different with values -1.6, -1.2, and -0.9. So a single line can not
                describe all of the points.
                </p>
                <p>
                Interpolation is to consider a line only between the two points surrounding
                the point of interest. The time of interest <m>t=35</m> is between the 
                times <m>t=20</m> and <m>t=40</m>.
                So we will use the points at those times, <m>(20, 4.8)</m> and <m>(40, 3.6)</m>,
                to define our approximating model for all times <m>t \in [20,40]</m>.
                We use these to find the rate of change
                <me> \frac{\Delta V}{\Delta t} = \frac{3.6-4.8}{40-20} = \frac{-1.2}{20} = -0.06. </me>
                </p>
                <p>
                Knowing the rate of change and either end-point, we can get an equation 
                for the line.
                If we use the point <m>(20, 4.8)</m>, then the point<ndash />slope
                equation of the line is given by
                <me> \frac{V-4.8}{t-20} = -0.06 \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad
                V = -0.06(t-20) + 4.8.</me>
                Using a time <m>t=35</m>, we can approximate the value for <m>V</m>:
                <me>V = -0.06(35-20) + 4.8 = -0.06(15) + 4.8 = 3.9.</me>
                </p>
            </solution>
        </example>
	</subsection>
	
	<!-- Testing for Linearity -->
	<subsection>
		<title>Testing for Linearity</title>
		
		<p>
		Given some data involving two variables, we want to decide if those data follow a linear relation.
		We do this by testing whether the statement in the definition is satisfied.
		</p>
		
		<example>
			<p>
			Consider the simple dataset consisting of four points illustrated in the table.
			Determine if <m>y</m> is a linear function of <m>x</m>.
			</p>
			
            <table xml:id="table-test-linear-ex-1">
                <tabular top="major" halign="center">
                    <row bottom="minor">
                        <cell><m>i</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>x_i</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>y_i</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row><cell>1</cell><cell>0.20</cell><cell>0.48</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>2</cell><cell>0.45</cell><cell>0.45</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>3</cell><cell>0.60</cell><cell>0.40</cell></row>
                    <row bottom="major"><cell>4</cell><cell>0.80</cell><cell>0.36</cell></row>
                </tabular>
                <caption>Dataset to illustrate testing if data are linear.</caption>
            </table>
            
            <p>
            To test whether the definition of a linear function is satisfied, we need to
            check the slope between any two points. This corresponds to computing six different slopes,
            shown in the next table.
            </p>
            <table xml:id="table-test-linear-ex-1-slopes">
                <tabular top="major" halign="center">
                    <row bottom="minor" halign="center">
                        <cell>Comparison: <m>i</m><ndash/><m>j</m></cell>
                        <cell>Slope: <m>\displaystyle m_{i,j}=\frac{y_j-y_i}{x_j-x_i}</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1-2</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{1,2} = \frac{y_2-y_1}{x_2-x_1} = \frac{0.45-0.48}{0.45-0.20} = -0.12</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1-3</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{1,3} = \frac{y_3-y_1}{x_3-x_1} = \frac{0.40-0.48}{0.60-0.20} = -0.20</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>1-4</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{1,4} = \frac{y_4-y_1}{x_4-x_1} = \frac{0.36-0.48}{0.80-0.20} = -0.20</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2-3</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{2,3} = \frac{y_3-y_2}{x_3-x_2} = \frac{0.40-0.45}{0.60-0.45} = -0.333\ldots</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>2-4</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{2,4} = \frac{y_4-y_2}{x_4-x_2} = \frac{0.36-0.45}{0.80-0.45} = -0.257\ldots</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="major">
                        <cell>3-4</cell>
                        <cell><m>\displaystyle m_{3,4} = \frac{y_4-y_3}{x_4-x_3} = \frac{0.36-0.40}{0.80-0.60} = -0.20</m></cell>
                    </row>
                </tabular>
                <caption>Dataset to illustrate testing if data are linear.</caption>
            </table>
            
            <p>
            Notice that the computed values for the slope between points are <em>not</em> always the same value.
            So these data do <em>not</em> satisfy a linear relation.
            However, notice that those pairings that do not include <m>i=2</m> all result in slopes <m>m=-0.20</m>.
            It is the second point <m>i=2</m> that makes these data fail to be linear.
            </p>
            
            <p>
            The graphical visualization of the data reinforces why the data are not linear.
            It is possible to draw a line going through the points <m>i=1,3,4</m>, but that line
            fails to go through the point <m>i=2</m>.
            </p>
            
            <sidebyside>
              <caption>Plot illustrating data from Table<nbsp /><xref ref="table-test-linear-ex-1" />
              with the line passing through points 1, 3 and 4, but not 2.</caption>
              <image>
                <description>One point is not collinear with the other three points.</description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}[auto]
                \pgfmathsetmacro{\sx}{5}
                \pgfmathsetmacro{\sy}{10}

                \draw ($ (\sx*-0.1,\sy*0.54) $) -- ($ (\sx*1.1, \sy*0.3) $);
                \draw ($ (\sx*0,\sy*0.55) $) -- ($ (\sx*0, \sy*0.25) $);
                \draw ($ (\sx*-0.1,\sy*0.3) $) -- ($ (\sx*1.1, \sy*0.3) $);
          
                \foreach \x in {0.2, 0.4, 0.6, 0.8, 1.0}
                  \draw (\sx*\x cm,\sy*0.31) -- (\sx*\x cm,\sy*0.29cm) node[anchor=north,fill=white] {$\x$};

                \foreach \y in {0.35, 0.4, 0.45, 0.5}
                  \draw (\sx*0.02, \sy*\y ) -- (\sx*-0.02, \sy*\y) node[anchor=east, fill=white] {$\y$};
          
                \foreach \x/\y in { 0.2/0.48, 0.45/0.45, 0.6/0.4, 0.8/0.36 }
                  \fill (\sx*\x, \sy*\y) circle (2pt);

                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
              </image>
            </sidebyside>

		</example>
		
		<p>
		When checking a collection of points to determine if they are <term>collinear</term> (on the same line),
		we do not need to check all of the pairs of points. It is enough to choose one point, and then compare the slopes between
		that point and each of the other points. If those all agree, then the points will be collinear.
		Alternatively, it is also acceptable to compute the slope for each consecutive pair of points.
		This is a consequence of the following theorem.
		</p>
		
		<theorem>
			<statement>
				<p>
				Given three points <m>(x_1,y_1)</m>, <m>(x_2,y_2)</m> and <m>(x_3,y_3)</m> with distinct <m>x</m> values,
				if we define the slopes <m>\displaystyle m_{i,j} = \frac{y_j-y_i}{x_j-x_i}</m>, then 
				<me>m_{2,3} = \frac{x_3-x_1}{x_3-x_2} \cdot m_{1,3} - \frac{x_2-x_1}{x_3-x_2} \cdot m_{1,2}.</me>
				In particular, if <m>m_{1,3}=m_{1,2}=m</m>, then <m>m_{2,3}=m</m>.
				</p>
			</statement>
			<proof>
			<p>
			This proof uses the strategy of adding and subtracting an especially chosen value that
			will allow us to rewrite <m>m_{2,3}</m> in terms of the formulas for <m>m_{1,2}</m> and <m>m_{1,3}</m>.
			We know that <m>y_3-y_1 = m_{1,3}(x_3-x_1)</m> and <m>y_2-y_1 = m_{1,2}(x_2-x_1)</m>.
			So adding and subtracting <m>y_1</m> in the numerator of <m>m_{2,3}</m> we find
			<me>
			\begin{aligned}
			m_{2,3} &amp;= \frac{y_3-y_2}{x_3-x_2} = \frac{(y_3-y_1)-(y_2-y_1)}{x_3-x_2} \\
			&amp;= \frac{m_{1,3}(x_3-x_1) - m_{1,2}(x_2-x_1)}{x_3-x_2} \\
			&amp;= \frac{x_3-x_1}{x_3-x_2} \cdot m_{1,3} - \frac{x_2-x_1}{x_3-x_2} \cdot m_{1,2}
			\end{aligned}
			</me>
			In the case that <m>m_{1,2}=m_{1,3}=m</m>, then we can use a common factor:
			<me>m_{2,3} = \left( \frac{x_3-x_1}{x_3-x_2} - \frac{x_2-x_1}{x_3-x_2} \right) \cdot m
			= \frac{(x_3-x_1)-(x_2-x_1)}{x_3-x_2} \cdot m = m</me>
			</p>
			</proof>
		</theorem>
		
		<p>
		So in the previous example, we really only needed to compute <m>m_{1,2}</m>, <m>m_{1,3}</m> and <m>m_{1,4}</m>.
		Because <m>m_{1,3}=m_{1,4}</m> we know that the points 1, 3 and 4 were collinear. But because <m>m_{1,2}</m> was
		different, we knew immediately that the point 2 falls off of the line.
		</p>
		
		<example>
			<title>Testing for Proportionality and Linearity</title>
			
			<p>Consider two variables <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> that are measured under four
			different states, as recorded in the following table. Determine if these data
			are consistent with a proportional or linear model.
			</p>
			
            <table xml:id="table-test-linear-ex-2">
                <tabular top="major" align="center">
                    <row bottom="minor" >
                        <cell><m>i</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>x_i</m></cell>
                        <cell><m>y_i</m></cell>
                    </row>
                    <row><cell>1</cell><cell>0.2</cell><cell>0.3</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>2</cell><cell>0.4</cell><cell>0.5</cell></row>
                    <row><cell>3</cell><cell>0.8</cell><cell>0.9</cell></row>
                    <row bottom="major"><cell>4</cell><cell>1.6</cell><cell>1.7</cell></row>
                </tabular>
                <caption>Second dataset to illustrate testing if data are linear.</caption>
            </table>
            
            <p>
            For a real application, you would not compute values by hand; 
            you would use a computational tool, such as a calculator or spreadsheet,
            which can perform many calculations at essentially one time.
            </p>
            <p>
            Nearly all spreadsheets use a grid system with columns labeled by letters and rows labeled by numbers.
            Each rectangle in the sheet is called a cell and stores either a value or text.
            The value can be a formula based on other cells by typing an equal sign followed
            by a formula. References to the values of other cells in the formula are accomplished
            by using the column letter followed by the row number.
            </p>
            <p>
            While we are at it, let us also illustrate how we could determine if the data have a
            proportional relation in addition to testing the more general linear relation.
            We will compute the ratio of <m>y/x</m> and observe if it is constant and then
            compute the ratio of changes <m>(y_j-y_i)/(x_j-x_i)</m> for consecutive points
            and observe if that is constant.
            A completed spreadsheet is shown, once showing formulas that you would type and
            another showing the numeric results. (Technically, you only type a formula for the 
            first entry; then you copy and paste the result in the other cells and it will
            adjust the references appropriately.)
            </p>
            <sidebyside>
                <caption>Automatic calculation of ratio and slope based on data in a table using a spreadsheet.</caption>
                <tabular>
                <row>
                <cell>
                <image width="80%" source="images/lin_model_spreadsheet_formulas.png">
                    <description>Image showing a spreadsheet table with data and formulas used to compute 
                    ratio and slope.</description>
                </image>
                </cell></row>
                <row><cell>
                <image width="80%" source="images/lin_model_spreadsheet_results.png">
                    <description>Image showing a spreadsheet table with data and values of  
                    ratio and slope computed using formulas.</description>
                </image>
                </cell></row>
                </tabular>
            </sidebyside>
            <p>
            Because the ratio of variables was changing, we know that <m>y</m> is not proportional to <m>x</m>.
            However, because the ratio of change for the variables is constant, we know
            that <m>y</m> <em>is</em> a linear function of <m>x</m> with a slope <m>m=1</m>.
            Using the first point as our reference, <m>(x_1,y_1) = (0.2,0.3)</m>, we can write
            an equation of our line.
            <me>
            y = y_1+m(x-x_1) = 0.3 + 1.(x-0.2) = x+0.1
            </me>
            You can easily verify that this formula is correct since for every data point,
            if you add 0.1 to the <m>x</m>-value, you get the <m>y</m>-value.
            </p>
		</example>
	</subsection>
</section>