<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="logarithmic-scales">
    <title>Properties of Logarithms</title>

    <subsection>
        <title>Overview</title>
        
        <p>
        We previously learned that logarithms are the inverse functions of exponential
        functions. In this section, we will further develop our understanding of
        logarithms by considering a logarithmic number line. This new number line
        has the property that what we normally think of as addition is interpreted
        in the context of multiplication, resulting from the fact that when exponentials
        are multiplied, the powers are added. This interpretation allows us to
        understand the basic properties of logarithms.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        In addition, we will learn that when exponential and power functions
        can be plotted with logarithmic scale axes, the resulting transformed graph
        will appear linear. Not only will this allow us to identify from data whether
        a power function or exponential function is appropriate, but by finding the
        appropriate equation of a line (in the transformed variables), we can find
        the equation of the actual function using the properties of the logarithm.
        </p>
        
    </subsection>
    
    <!-- Fundamental properties of logarithms -->
    <subsection>
        <title>Logarithmic Number Lines</title>
        
        <p>
        The standard number line is also called an arithmetic number line.
        Spacing between numbers is based on addition.
        That is, there is a length called the unit length that represents
        the space between consecutive whole numbers, and in particular it is the
        distance between the numbers 0 and 1 on the number line.
        A consequence of this spacing of numbers is that
        the space between any two numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>
        on the number line is exactly the same as the spacing
        between <m>0</m> and <m>b-a</m>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Adding numbers on an arithmetic number line corresponds geometrically 
        to combining the lengths. One way to see this is to consider two identical
        number lines and two numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>.
        Take the first number line and find the number <m>a</m> on that number line.
        Now, take the second number line and move it so that the number 0
        (which is the <term>additive identity</term>) is exactly aligned with the
        number <m>a</m> on the first number line.
        Find the second number <m>b</m> on the shifted number line and
        see what number appears next to it on the original number line.
        That number will be <m>a+b</m>.
        </p>
        
        <figure xml:id="fig-number-line-addition">
            <caption>Addition of the numbers 8 and -3 using arithmetic number lines ends at <m>8+-3=5</m>.</caption>
            <image>
                <description>
                Addition of the numbers 8 and -3 using arithmetic number lines.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}[x=0.5cm]
                \draw[<->] (-4.5,0) -- (12.5,0);
                \foreach \x in {-4, -3, ..., 12}
                    \draw (\x,0.1) -- (\x,-0.1) node[below] {\x};
                \draw [very thick, red, ->] (0,0) -- (8,0);
                \draw[<->] (-4.5,-1) -- (12.5,-1);
                \foreach \x in {-12, -11, ..., 4}
                    \draw ($ (\x+8,-1+0.1) $) -- ($ (\x+8,-1-0.1) $) node[below] {\x};
                \draw [very thick, red, ->] (8,-1) -- (5,-1);
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </figure>
        
        <p>
        A logarithmic number line is a number line that is designed for
        multiplication instead of addition.
        The number 1, which is the multiplicative identity, represents the origin.
        The logarithmic number line involves only positive numbers and
        is designed so that the spacing between values corresponds to
        the ratio of numbers (instead of the difference).
        That is, given two positive numbers <m>a>0</m> and <m>b>0</m>,
        the spacing between the numbers is the same as the space
        between 1 and <m>b/a</m>.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        The consequence of this construction is that geometric addition corresponds
        to multiplication of numbers. That is, if we want to multiply two numbers
        <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>, you start with one logarithmic number line and
        position the second line so 1 is aligned with <m>a</m>. Finding the number
        <m>b</m> on the second line will correspond to the location of <m>ab</m>
        on the original line.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-lognumber-line-multiplication">
            <caption>Multiplication of the numbers 3 and 5 using logarithmic number lines ends at <m>3 \cdot 5=15</m>.</caption>
            <image>
                <description>
                Multiplication of the numbers 3 and 5 using logarithmic number lines.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}[x=2cm]
                \draw[<->] (-0.5,0) -- (5,0);
                \foreach \x in {1, 2, ..., 30}
                    \draw ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(2)},0.1) $) -- ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(2)},-0.1) $);
                \foreach \x in {1, 2, ..., 10, 12, 15, 20}
                    \node[below] at ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(2)},-0.1) $) {\x};
                \draw [very thick, red, ->] ($ ({ln(1)/ln(2)},0) $) -- ($ ({ln(3)/ln(2)},0) $);

                \draw[<->] (-0.5,-1) -- (5,-1);
                \foreach \x in {1, 2, ..., 10}
                    \draw ($ ({ln(3*\x)/ln(2)},-0.9) $) -- ($ ({ln(3*\x)/ln(2)},-1.1) $);
                \foreach \x in {1, 2, ..., 10}
                    \node[below] at ($ ({ln(3*\x)/ln(2)},-1.1) $) {\x};
                \draw [very thick, red, ->] ($ ({ln(3)/ln(2)},-1) $) -- ($ ({ln(15)/ln(2)},-1) $);

                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </figure>
        
        <p>
        This number line exactly corresponds to the idea of the logarithm functions.
        Consider an exponential base <m>b</m>. The integer powers of <m>b</m> will 
        be equally spaced on the logarithmic number line.
        The unit length will correspond to the spacing between the origin 1 and the 
        base <m>b</m> which is also the spacing between all integer powers of <m>b</m>.
        Adjacent to the logarithmic number line, put an arithmetic number line 
        so that the origin 0 is adjacent to the 1 on the logarithmic line
        and the number 1 is adjacent to the base <m>b</m> on the logarithmic line.
        The exponential function with base <m>b</m>, <m>\exp_b(x)</m>, is the
        mapping from the arithmetic line to the logarithmic line.
        The logarithm function with base <m>b</m>, <m>\log_b(x)</m>, is the inverse
        mapping from the logarithmic line back to the arithmetic line.
        The following figure illustrates this with a base <m>b=3</m>.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-logarithm-by-numberline">
            <caption>The logarithm base <m>b=3</m> uses the logarithmic scale with a unit length corresponding to <m>b=3</m>.
            </caption>
            <image>
                <description>
                Logarithm base 3 as appearing on a number line.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}[x=2.5cm]
                \draw[<->] (-0.5,0) -- (3.5,0)
                    node [right] {$u=\exp_3(x)$};
                \foreach \x in {1, 2, ..., 30}
                    \draw ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(3)},-0.1) $) -- ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(3)},0.1) $);
                \foreach \x in {1,2,...,10,12,15,20,27}
                    \node[below] at ($ ({ln(\x)/ln(3)},-0.1) $) {\x};

                \draw[<->] (-0.5,-1) -- (3.5,-1)
                    node [right] {$x=\log_3(u)$};
                \foreach \x in {0, 1, 2, 3}
                    \draw [very thick] (\x, -0.1) -- (\x, 0.1);
                \foreach \x in {0, 1, 2, 3}
                    \draw (\x, -0.9) -- (\x, -1.1)
                    node [below] {\x};
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </figure>
        
        
        <definition>
        <statement>
        For a base <m>b>0</m> with <m>b \ne 1</m>, we define
        <m>\log_b(x)</m> to be that number <m>a</m> such that <m>x=\exp_b(a)=b^a</m>.
        <me> \log_b(x) = a \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad \exp_b(a)=x \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad b^a = x </me>
        </statement>
        </definition>
        
        <p>
        Because multiplication on the logarithmic scale is identical to 
        addition on the arithmetic scale, the logarithm function inherits a 
        corresponding property. Also, division is the inverse operation to 
        multiplication in the same way that subtraction is the inverse operation
        to addition. Finally, because powers correspond to repeated multiplication,
        any power <m>a^p</m> in a logarithmic scale will correspond to a position
        that is exactly <m>p</m> times the logarithm of <m>a</m>.
        These three features provide the three key properties of every logarithm
        function, which are summarized in the following theorem.
        </p>
        
        <theorem>
        <statement>
        For any base <m>b>0</m> with <m>b \ne 1</m>, 
        <md> 
            <mrow> \log_b(u \cdot v) &amp;= \log_b(u) + \log_b(v) </mrow>
            <mrow> \log_b(u \div v) &amp;= \log_b(u) - \log_b(v) </mrow>
            <mrow> \log_b(u^p) &amp;= p \cdot \log_b(u) </mrow>
        </md>
        </statement>
        </theorem>
        
        <p>
        These properties are exactly the inverse properties of exponential functions.
        </p>
        
        <theorem>
        <statement>
        For any base <m>b>0</m> with <m>b \ne 1</m>, 
        <md> 
            <mrow> \exp_b(x+y) &amp;= \exp_b(x) \cdot \exp_b(y) </mrow>
            <mrow> \exp_b(x-y) &amp;= \exp_b(x) \div \exp_b(y) </mrow>
            <mrow> \exp_b(x \cdot y) &amp;= (\exp_b(x))^y </mrow>
        </md>
        </statement>
        <proof>
            <p>
            The proof of these properties is just interpreting properties of powers
            in the context of exponential functions.
            </p>
            <md>
                <mrow> \exp_b(x+y) = b^{x+y} = b^x \cdot b^y = \exp_b(x) \cdot \exp_b(y) </mrow>
                <mrow> \exp_b(x-y) = b^{x-y} = \frac{b^x}{b^y} = \exp_b(x) \div \exp_b(y) </mrow>
                <mrow> \exp_b(x \cdot y) = b^{x \cdot y} = (b^x)^y = (\exp_b(x))^y </mrow>
            </md>
        </proof>
        </theorem>
        
        <p>
        The logarithm properties can be used to find logarithms of a quantity in terms
        of its factors. This can be illustrated using numbers as well as formulas.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
        Given that <m>\log_3(2) \approx 0.6309</m> and <m>\log_3(5) \approx 1.4650</m>,
        determine each of the following:
        <ol>
            <li><m>\log_3(10)</m></li>
            <li><m>\log_3(\frac{27}{5})</m></li>
            <li><m>\log_3(\frac{32}{125})</m></li>
        </ol>
        </statement>
        
        <solution>
        <ol>
            <li>
            We start by factoring 10 as <m>10=2 \cdot 5</m>. So we use the
            product rule for logarithms:
            <me> \log_3(10) = \log_3(2 \cdot 5) = \log_3(2) + \log_3(5).</me>
            At this point, we use our approximations:
            <me> \log_3(10) \approx 0.6309 + 1.4650 = 2.0959. </me>
            </li>
            <li>
            Because <m>\frac{27}{5}</m> is a quotient, we know that we will
            use the quotient rule for logarithms.
            <me> \log_3(\frac{27}{5}) = \log_3(27) - \log_3(5) </me>
            Because 27 is a power of 3, <m>27 = 3^3</m>, we know <m>\log_3(27) = 3</m>.
            Consequently, we find with our approximations that
            <me> \log_3(\frac{27}{5}) = 3 - \log_3(5) 
            \approx 3 - 1.4650 = 1.5350. </me>
            </li>
            <li>
            Because <m>\frac{32}{125}</m> is a quotient, we will use the 
            quotient rule for logarithms. We also need to consider the
            prime factorizations, <m>32 = 2^5</m> and <m>125=5^3</m>.
            Together, these allow us to compute
            <me> \log_3(\frac{32}{125}) = \log_3(32) - \log_3(125)
            = \log_3(2^5) - \log_3(5^3) = 5 \log_3(2) - 3 \log_3(5). </me>
            Using our approximations, we find
            <me> \log_3(\frac{32}{125}) \approx 5(0.6309) - 3(1.4650)
            = -1.2405. </me>
            </li>
        </ol>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            <p>
            Expand the expression <m>\displaystyle \log_b(\frac{u\cdot v^k}{w^n})</m> using properties of logarithms.
            </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            The properties of logarithms depend on recognizing the operation forming
            the expression as input. Our expression <m>\displaystyle \frac{u \cdot v^k}{w^n}</m> involves division,
            so we must use the rule for the logarithm of a quotient.
            <me> \log_b(\frac{u \cdot v^k}{w^n}) = \log_b(u \cdot v^k) - \log_b(w^n). </me>
            We repeat the process until rules no longer apply.
            The expression <m>u \cdot v^k</m> is a product, so the rule for a logarithm of a product gives
            <me> \log_b(\frac{u \cdot v^k}{w^n}) = \log_b(u) + \log_b(v^k) - \log_b(w^n). </me>
            The expression <m>v^k</m> and <m>w^n</m> are both powers, so the rule for a logarithm of a power gives
            <me> \log_b(\frac{u \cdot v^k}{w^n}) = \log_b(u) + k \cdot \log_b(v) - n \cdot \log_b(w). </me>
            This is completely expanded.
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        The reverse process can also be performed, taking an expression involving multiple logarithms
        that are added or subtracted to find a single expression involving one logarithm.
        The key to doing this properly is to be sure that order of operations actually gives
        you a sum of two logarithms (to become the logarithm of a product), 
        a difference of two logarithms (to become the logarithm of a quotient),
        or a product of a value times a logarithm (to become the logarithm of a power).
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            <p>
            Simplify the expression <m>\log(x) - 4\log(y) + 2 \log(z)</m> using properties of logarithms.
            </p>
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Order of operations tells us that the expression first involves the product of 4 and <m>\log(y)</m>.
            This can be rewritten as the logarithm of <m>y</m> to a power, <m>4 \log(y) = \log(y^4)</m>.
            Similarly, the next operation would be the product of 2 and <m>\log(z)</m> which
            can be rewritten <m>2 \log(z) = \log(z^2)</m>. We now have
            <me> \log(x) - 4 \log(y) + 2 \log(z) = \log(x) - \log(y^4) + \log(z^2). </me>
            Order of operations put addition and subtraction at the same priority, so we must interpret
            this left-to-right. So we have a difference of <m>\log(x)</m> and <m>\log(y^4)</m>,
            which can be rewritten as the logarithm of a quotient,
            <me> \log(x) - 4 \log(y) + 2 \log(z) = \log(\frac{x}{y^4}) + \log(z^2). </me>
            Finally, we have the sum of two logarithms, which can be rewritten as the logarithm of a product,
            <me> \log(x) - 4 \log(y) + 2 \log(z) = \log(\frac{x}{y^4} \cdot z^2) = \log(\frac{xz^2}{y^4}). </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        Scientific calculators have two logarithm functions.
        One logarithm that is used most often for data involves base <m>b=10</m>,
        also called the common logarithm. This is especially useful as it relates 
        to scientific notation. Every positive number can be written in
        scientific notation as <m>m \times 10^p</m> where <m>1 \le m \lt 10</m>
        and <m>p</m> is an integer. Then the common logarithm will be
        <me> \log_{10}(m \times 10^p) = p + \log_{10}(m) </me>
        with a value between <m>p</m> and <m>p+1</m>.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <md>
            <mrow> \log_{10}(3.25) &amp; \approx 0.5119 </mrow> 
            <mrow> \log_{10}(3.25 \times 10^4) &amp; = 4 + \log_{10}(3.25) \approx 4.5119 </mrow>
            <mrow> \log_{10}(3.25 \times 10^{-3}) &amp; = -3 + \log_{10}(3.25) \approx -2.4881 </mrow> 
        </md>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        While a common logarithm is convenient for representing numbers in terms
        of their order of magnitude, mathematics usually considers the 
        natural logarithm with base <m>e \approx 2.7182818285</m>.
        The reason for this choice will be made clear as we learn calculus.
        </p>

    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
        <title>Semi<ndash />Log and Log<ndash />Log Plots</title>
        
        <p>
        When data grow multiplicatively, such as in exponential growth,
        a logarithmic scale is more appropriate than a standard arithmetic (linear) scale.
        Instead of plotting the data in a standard Cartesian plane, one or both axes
        are replaced with a logarithmic number line.
        A log<ndash />log plot has both axes using a logarithmic scale.
        A semi-log plot has only one axis changed to a logarithmic scale.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        In addition to helping visualize data that have a wide range of 
        order of magnitudes (the power in scientific notation), logarithmic
        scales provide a useful transformation. In particular, power functions
        and exponential functions transform into linear functions
        under appropriate logarithmic transformations. This section explains
        how this can be used.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        An elementary power function is a function where the independent variable
        is raised to a constant power <m>p \ne 0</m>, usually a rational number. 
        <me> y = \mathrm{pow}_{p}(x) = x^p </me>
        Every other power function is a constant
        multiple of an elementary power function,
        <me> y = A \cdot x^p, </me>
        where <m>A</m> is some constant value.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        An elementary exponential function is a function where a constant base
        <m>b>0</m> with <m>b \ne 1</m> is raised to power given by the independent
        variable.
        <me> y = \exp_{b}(x) = b^x </me>
        Every other exponential function is a constant multiple of
        an elementary exponential function,
        <me> y = A \cdot b^{x}, </me>
        where <m>A</m> is a constant.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Be sure that you see the difference between a power function, where the
        base is the variable and the power is a constant, and an exponential
        function where the base is a constant and the power is the variable.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Now, consider what happens if you use a logarithm to transform
        the dependent variable in each case. This corresponds to making
        the <m>y</m>-axis a logarithmic scale.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        Suppose that <m>y</m> is a power function with <m>A>0</m>:
        <me> y = A \cdot x^{p}. </me>
        Under a transformation, we have <m>v = \log(y)</m> so
        that the power function becomes:
        <me> v = \log(y) = \log(A \cdot x^{p}) = \log(A) + \log(x^{p})
        = \log(A) + p \log(x) </me>
        Notice that the independent variable is also in a logarithm,
        so we make the <m>x</m>-axis a logarithmic scale corresponding
        to a transformation <m>u = \log(x)</m>.
        In the transformed variables, we have
        <me> v = \log(A) + p \cdot u. </me>
        That is, a power function in linear in a log<ndash />log graph.
        The slope of the line corresponds to the power <m>p</m>.
        </p>

        <p>
        Suppose that <m>y</m> is an exponential function with <m>A>0</m>
        and base <m>b>0</m>:
        <me> y = A \cdot b^{x}. </me>
        Under a transformation, we have <m>v = \log(y)</m> so
        that the exponential function becomes:
        <me> v = \log(y) = \log(A \cdot b^x) = \log(A) + \log(b^x)
        = \log(A) + x \log(b) </me>
        This time, the independent variable is not in a logarithm,
        so the <m>x</m>-axis is kept in a standard axis.
        An exponential function appears linear in a semi-log graph.
        The slope of the line is the logarithm of the base.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            Find the power function passing through the points
            <m>(1,5)</m> and <m>(4,30)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            A power function is of the form <m>y=A \cdot x^{p}</m>,
            so we will need to find the constants <m>A</m> and <m>p</m>.
            From above, we know that a log<ndash />log transform will 
            make this linear, so we create transformed points
            with <m>u = \log_{10}(x)</m> and <m>v = \log_{10}(y)</m>
            so that <m>v</m> will be a linear function of <m>u</m>:
            <me> v = \log_{10}(y) = \log_{10}(A \cdot x^{p}) = \log_{10}(A) + p \cdot \log_{10}(x)
            = \log_{10}(A) + p \cdot u. </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            The points become: 
            <md>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(1,5) \quad \rightarrow \quad (u,v) \approx (0, 0.69897) </mrow>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(4,30) \quad \rightarrow \quad (u,v) \approx (0.60206, 1.47712) </mrow>
            </md>
            The slope of the transformed points gives us our power:
            <me>
             p = \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta u} = \frac{1.47712 - 0.69897}{0.60206-0} = 1.2925.
            </me>
            The <m>v</m>-intercept is the logarithm of the constant multiple:
            <me>
            \log_{10}(A) = 0.69897 \quad \Rightarrow \quad A = 10^{0.69897} = 5.
            </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            The desired power function is approximately given by
            <me> y = 5 \cdot x^{1.2925} </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>

        <example>
        <statement>
            Find the exponential function passing through the points
            <m>(1,5)</m> and <m>(4,30)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            An exponential function is of the form <m>y=A \cdot b^{x}</m>,
            so we will need to find the constant <m>A</m> and the base <m>b</m>.
            From above, we know that a semi-log transform will 
            make this linear, so we create transformed points (only transforming vertical points)
            with <m>u = x</m> and <m>v = \log_{10}(y)</m>
            so that <m>v</m> will be a linear function of <m>u</m>:
            <me> v = \log_{10}(y) = \log_{10}(A \cdot b^{x}) = \log_{10}(A) + x \cdot \log_{10}(b)
            = \log_{10}(A) + \log_{10}(b) \cdot u. </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            The points become: 
            <md>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(1,5) \quad \rightarrow \quad (u,v) \approx (1, 0.69897) </mrow>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(4,30) \quad \rightarrow \quad (u,v) \approx (4, 1.47712) </mrow>
            </md>
            The slope of the transformed points gives us the logarithm of our base:
            <me>
             \log_{10}(b) = \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta u} = \frac{1.47712 - 0.69897}{4-1} \approx 0.25938.
            </me>
            The equation relating <m>(u,v)</m> is given by
            <me>
            v = 0.25938(u-1) + 0.69897 = 0.25938 u + 0.43959.
            </me>
            Because our logarithm represents a power of 10, we can find the base <m>b</m> 
            and the constant <m>A</m>:
            <md>
            <mrow> \log_{10}(b)=0.25938 \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad b = 10^{0.25938} \approx 1.8171, </mrow>
            <mrow> \log_{10}(A)=0.43959 \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad A = 10^{0.43959} \approx 2.7516. </mrow>
            </md>
            Consequently, our model can be written as an exponential function
            <me>
            y = 2.7516 \cdot (1.8171)^{x}.
            </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        The previous examples illustrated how to find approximate solutions.
        Whenever you replace an exact expression with a rounded decimal value,
        you are doing an approximation. The same problems can be solved exactly
        by using properties of logarithms.
        </p>

        <example>
        <statement>
            Find the exact power function passing through the points
            <m>(1,5)</m> and <m>(4,30)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            A power function is linear after a log<ndash />log transform.
            We find transformed points <m>(x,y) \mapsto (u,v)</m> where
            <m>u = \log(x)</m> and <m>v = \log(y)</m> (for any base).
            Our transformed points are
            <md>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(1,5) \quad \mapsto \quad (u,v) = (\log(1),\log(5)), </mrow>
                <mrow> (x,y)=(4,30) \quad \mapsto \quad (u,v) = (\log(4),\log(30)). </mrow>
            </md>
            We can compute the slope of the relation for <m>(u,v)</m>,
            <me> \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta u} = \frac{\log(30)-\log(5)}{\log(4)-\log(1)}. </me>
            Using the properties of logarithms, we can replace the difference of logarithms
            by a logarithm of a quotient to find a new representation of the slope,
            <me> \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta u} = \frac{\log(30/5)}{\log(4/1)} = \frac{\log(6)}{\log(4)}. </me>
            Note that there is no additional simplification.
            </p>
            
            <p>
            Knowing the slope, we can find the equation of the line for <m>(u,v)</m> using 
            the point<ndash/>slope form.
            <me>v - \log(5) = \frac{\log(6)}{\log(4)} (u-\log(1)). </me>
            We can use this equation to find the power function in terms of <m>(x,y)</m>
            by replacing <m>v=\log(y)</m> and <m>u=\log(x)</m>,
            <me>\log(y) - \log(5) = \frac{\log(6)}{\log(4)} (\log(x)-\log(1)). </me>
            Again, we use the properties of logarithms to combine terms,
            <me>\log(y/5) = \frac{\log(6)}{\log(4)} (\log(x/1)). </me>
            Using <m>p=\log(6)/\log(4)</m> and the property <m>p \log(x) = \log(x^p)</m>,
            we obtain
            <me>\log(y/5) = \log(x^{p}), </me>
            which in turn means that
            <me> \frac{y}{5} = x^p \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad y = 5 x^{\log(6)/\log(4)}. </me>
            This matches our earlier calculation since <m>p = \log(6)/\log(4) \approx 1.2925</m>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>

        <example>
        <statement>
            Find the exact exponential function passing through the points
            <m>(1,5)</m> and <m>(4,30)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            An exponential function is linear after a semi-log transform.
            We create transformed points <m>(x,y) \mapsto (x,v)</m> where <m>v = \log(y)</m> (any base).
            Our transformed points, given by
            <md>
                <mrow> (x,y) = (1,5) \quad \mapsto \quad (x,v) = (1,\log(5)), </mrow>
                <mrow> (x,y) = (4,30) \quad \mapsto \quad (x,v) = (4, \log(30)), </mrow>
            </md>
            will have a linear relation.
            We find the slope of the transformed point,
            <me> \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta x} = \frac{\log(30)-\log(5)}{4-1} = \frac{\log(6)}{3}. </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            Knowing the slope allows us to write down the equation of the line for <m>(x,v)</m>:
            <me> v-\log(5) = \frac{\log(6)}{3} (x-1). </me>
            We can find the relation for <m>(x,y)</m> by rewriting <m>v=\log(y)</m> and then
            using the properties of logarithms to find our equation.
            <md>
                <mrow> \log(y)-\log(5) = \frac{\log(6)}{3}(x-1) </mrow>
                <mrow> \log(y/5) = \log(6) \cdot \frac{x-1}{3} = \log\Big(6^{(x-1)/3}\Big) </mrow>
                <mrow> \frac{y}{5} = 6^{(x-1)/3} </mrow>
                <mrow> y = 5 \cdot 6^{(x-1)/3} </mrow>
            </md>
            This final form does not look like an exponential function <m>A b^x</m> as written.
            Using the properties of powers (exponents), we could rewrite it:
            <md>
                <mrow>5 \cdot 6^{(x-1)/3} &amp;= 5 \cdot (6^{1/3})^{(x-1)} </mrow>
                <mrow> &amp;= 5 \cdot \frac{(\sqrt[3]{6})^x}{\sqrt[3]{6}} </mrow>
                <mrow> &amp;= \frac{5}{\sqrt[3]{6}} \cdot (\sqrt[3]{6})^x. </mrow>
            </md>
            Comparing this to our earlier approximation, we see that <m>A = \frac{5}{\sqrt[3]{6}} \approx 2.7516</m>
            and <m>b=\sqrt[3]{6} \approx 1.8171</m>.
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
    </subsection>
    
</section>