<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->

<section xml:id="periodic-models">
    <title>Periodic Models</title>

    <subsection>
        <title>Overview</title>

        <p>
        This section discusses periodic functions, specifically using
        the trigonometric functions of sine and cosine as models for periodic
        functions.
        A periodic function captures the idea of cycles that repeat perfectly
        and indefinitely.
        Oscillatory waves can be modeled with periodic functions, including
        sound, light and radio waves.
        The spiking patterns of a neuron can be modeled with periodic functions.
        Cyclic patterns in populations can even be modeled with periodic functions.
        </p>

        <p>
        Periodic functions are characterized by basic features.
        One of the most fundamental features is called the period, which is
        how much the input of the function needs to increase before the function
        exactly repeats its output.
        When a wave is observered spatially, the period of the function
        corresponds to the wavelength.
        When a wave is observed temporally (in time), the period of the function
        corresponds to the physical period, or the time between repeating cycles.
        </p>

        <p>

        </p>

    </subsection>

    <!-- Quick Overview of Sinusoidal Graphs -->
    <subsection>
        <title>A Barebones Review of Sine and Cosine</title>

        <p>
        The appendix has a much more detailed discussion of trigonometric functions.
        For our purposes, all that I really want to review is the oscillatory
        behavior of the sine and cosine functions as prototypes of periodic
        functions. One dynamical perspective of the graphs results from
        considering a point that moves around a unit circle at a steady speed.
        </p>

        <p>
        The point starts at the position <m>(1,0)</m>. We consider counter-clockwise
        rotation as positive motion and clockwise rotation as negative motion, and
        we measure the distance <m>x</m> the point travels along the circumference.
        (This is what the radian measure of an angle measures: the distance traveled
        on a unit circle.)
        The sine function gives from the vertical position of the point after
        traveling some distance along the circumference of the unit circle.
        The cosine function gives the horizontal position of the point.
        Thus, based on our starting point <m>(1,0)</m>, we have
        <me>\sin(0) = 0 \qquad \cos(0) = 1.</me>
        In addition, because both the horizontal and vertical coordinates of the unit
        circle remain between -1 and 1, we know that the sine and cosine oscillate
        between a minimum at -1 and a maximum at +1,
        <me>-1 \le \sin(x) \le 1 \qquad -1 \le \cos(x) \le 1. </me>
        </p>

        <image>
            <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}[thick,x=2.25cm,y=2.25cm]
                \draw[->] (-1.2,0) -- (1.2,0);
                \draw[->] (0,-1.2) -- (0,1.2);

                \draw (-1,-0.1) -- (-1,0.1);
                \draw (1,-0.1) -- (1,0.1);
                \draw ({cos(50)},-0.1) -- ({cos(50)},0.1)
                    node[pos=0,below] {$\cos(x)$};

                \draw (-0.1,-1) -- (0.1,-1);
                \draw (-0.1,1) -- (0.1,1);
                \draw (-0.1,{sin(50)}) -- (0.1,{sin(50)})
                    node[pos=0,left] {$\sin(x)$};

                \draw[thin] (0,0) circle (1);
                \draw[very thick, color=blue] (1.01,0) arc (0:50:1.01);
                \draw[thin, color=blue, ->] (1.05,0) arc (0:50:1.05)
                    node [pos=0.5, right] {$x$};

                \draw[fill] (50:1) circle (2pt);

                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
        </image>

        <p>
        As soon as the point travels a distance of <m>2\pi</m>, it has completed a full
        revolution of the circle and it is as though it is revisiting the same points.
        This is why the sine and cosine functions are periodic with a period <m>2 \pi</m>.
        </p>

        <image>
            <description>The graphs of cosine and sine functions.
            </description>
            <latex-image>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}[thick,domain=-2.2:8.2, samples=100, x=.7cm]
            \draw[->] (-2.2,0) -- (8.2,0) node[right] {$x$};
            \draw[->] (0,-1.4) -- (0,1.4) node[above] {$y$};
            \draw[color=blue] plot (\x,{cos(pi/2*\x r)});
            \draw[color=red] plot (\x,{sin(pi/2*\x r)});
            \draw (-0.1,1) -- (0.1,1) node[right] {1};
            \draw (-0.1,-1) -- (0.1,-1) node[right] {-1};

            \draw (-2, -0.1) -- (-2, 0.1) node[above] {$-\pi$};
            \draw (-1, -0.1) -- (-1, 0.1) node[above] {$-\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (1, -0.1) -- (1, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (2, -0.1) -- (2, 0.1) node[above] {$\pi$};
            \draw (3, -0.1) -- (3, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{3\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (4, -0.1) -- (4, 0.1) node[above] {$2 \pi$};
            \draw (5, -0.1) -- (5, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{5\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (6, -0.1) -- (6, 0.1) node[above] {$3 \pi$};
            \draw (7, -0.1) -- (7, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{7\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (8, -0.1) -- (8, 0.1) node[above] {$4 \pi$};

            \draw [color=blue] (8.5,1) -- (9,1) node [right] {$y=\cos(x)$};
            \draw [color=red] (8.5,0.6) -- (9,0.6) node [right] {$y=\sin(x)$};

            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
        </image>

        <p>
        As a consequence of their unit circle definitions,
        the sine and cosine functions are especially symmetric.
        For example, the cosine function is an <term>even function</term>,
        which means that if you reflect the graph horizontally over the <m>y</m>-axis,
        the graph is unchanged. This graphical view is expressed in an equation as
        <me> \cos(-x) = \cos(x). </me>
        That is, if the graph <m>y=\cos(x)</m> includes some point <m>(x,y)=(a,b)</m>,
        then the opposite point <m>(x,y)=(-a,b)</m>
        (changing only the <m>x</m>-coordinate) is also in the graph.
        </p>

        <image>
            <description>The cosine function is even (horizontal reflection symmetry).
            </description>
            <latex-image>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}[thick,domain=-4.2:4.2, samples=100, x=1cm, y=1.25cm]
            \draw[->] (-4.2,0) -- (4.2,0) node[right] {$x$};
            \draw[->] (0,-1.4) -- (0,1.4) node[above] {$y$};
            \draw[color=blue] plot (\x,{cos(pi/2*\x r)});
            \draw (-0.1,1) -- (0.1,1) node[right] {1};
            \draw (-0.1,-1) -- (0.1,-1) node[right] {-1};

            \draw (-4, -0.1) -- (-4, 0.1) node[above] {$-2\pi$};
            \draw (-3, -0.1) -- (-3, 0.1) node[above] {$-\frac{3\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (-2, -0.1) -- (-2, 0.1) node[above] {$-\pi$};
            \draw (-1, -0.1) -- (-1, 0.1) node[above] {$-\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (1, -0.1) -- (1, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (2, -0.1) -- (2, 0.1) node[above] {$\pi$};
            \draw (3, -0.1) -- (3, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{3\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (4, -0.1) -- (4, 0.1) node[above] {$2\pi$};

            \draw [color=blue] (4.5,1) -- (5,1) node [right] {$y=\cos(x)$};
            \draw[fill] (2.5, {cos(2.5*90)}) circle (2pt) node [right] {$(a,\cos(a))$};
            \draw[fill] (-2.5, {cos(-2.5*90)}) circle (2pt) node [left] {$(-a,\cos(-a))$};

            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
        </image>

        <p>
        How do you read or interpret that equation? On the left, we see the expression
        <m>\cos(-x)</m>. In the language of transformations, we have an original graph
        <m>y=\cos(x)</m>. This expression corresponds to a new relation <m>v=\cos(-u)</m>
        so that our transformed variables are <m>v=y</m> and <m>x=-u</m>. That is,
        <m>\cos(-x)</m> is the function that corresponds to changing all <m>x</m>-coordinates
        by multiplying by -1 (or switching positive/negative sides on the number line).
        So the equation is saying, on the left, if you take the graph of <m>\cos(x)</m>
        and flip all points from left-to-right, then this is exactly equal to the
        original graph. Again, note that changing variables to interpret the transformation
        is a convenience and not necessary. You should practice to where this extra
        step becomes unnecessary.
        </p>

        <p>
        While the cosine function is even, the sine function is an <term>odd function</term>.
        This means that if you do a horizontal reflection, instead of getting the original
        function, you instead get what would be equivalent to a vertical reflection. This
        is expressed mathematically by the equation
        <me> \sin(-x) = - \sin(x). </me>
        Do you see how each side of the equation represents a different transformation,
        and the equation says that the two different transformations result in the same thing?
        Graphically, this is the same as saying the graph has a rotational symmetry
        of 180 degrees or that the graph is symmetric across the origin. That is,
        if the graph of <m>y=\sin(x)</m> includes a point <m>(x,y)=(a,b)</m>, then the
        opposite point <m>(x,y)=(-a,-b)</m> (both change because going across the origin)
        is also on the graph.
        </p>

        <image>
            <description>The sine function is odd (symmetry across the origin).
            </description>
            <latex-image>
            <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}[thick,domain=-4.2:4.2, samples=100, x=1cm, y=1.25cm]
            \draw[->] (-4.2,0) -- (4.2,0) node[right] {$x$};
            \draw[->] (0,-1.4) -- (0,1.4) node[above] {$y$};
            \draw[color=red] plot (\x,{sin(pi/2*\x r)});
            \draw (-0.1,1) -- (0.1,1) node[right] {1};
            \draw (-0.1,-1) -- (0.1,-1) node[right] {-1};

            \draw (-4, -0.1) -- (-4, 0.1) node[above] {$-2\pi$};
            \draw (-3, -0.1) -- (-3, 0.1) node[above] {$-\frac{3\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (-2, -0.1) -- (-2, 0.1) node[above] {$-\pi$};
            \draw (-1, -0.1) -- (-1, 0.1) node[above] {$-\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (1, -0.1) -- (1, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (2, -0.1) -- (2, 0.1) node[above] {$\pi$};
            \draw (3, -0.1) -- (3, 0.1) node[above] {$\frac{3\pi}{2}$};
            \draw (4, -0.1) -- (4, 0.1) node[above] {$2\pi$};

            \draw [color=red] (4.5,1) -- (5,1) node [right] {$y=\sin(x)$};
            \draw[fill] (2.5, {sin(2.5*90)}) circle (2pt) node [left] {$(a,\sin(a))$};
            \draw[fill] (-2.5, {sin(-2.5*90)}) circle (2pt) node [right] {$(-a,\sin(-a))$};

            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image>
        </image>

        <p>
        Because a circle is rotationally symmetric,
        the sine and cosine graphs have the same shapes although they are shifted
        with respect to one another. If we took the graph of the cosine and
        shifted it to the right by the arc length corresponding to a quarter rotation,
        <m>\frac{1}{4}(2\pi) = \frac{\pi}{2}</m>,
        then we get the sine graph. This is given by either of the following equations.
        <md>
            <mrow>\cos(x-\frac{\pi}{2}) = \sin(x)</mrow>
            <mrow>\sin(x+\frac{\pi}{2}) = \cos(x)</mrow>
        </md>
        </p>

    </subsection>
    <subsection>
        <title>Periodic Functions</title>

        <definition>
            <title>Periodic Function</title>

            <statement>
                <p>
                A function <m>f</m> is <term>periodic</term> if there is a number <m>p</m>
                so that <m>f(x+p)=f(x)</m> for all <m>x</m>. The smallest such number <m>p</m>
                is called the <term>period</term> of the function.
                </p>
            </statement>
        </definition>

        <p>
        Waves are a good physical example of periodic behavior.
        (I'm thinking about steady rolling waves or ripples, not breaking waves that do
        not pass the vertical line test but are much more fun.)
        If we took a snapshot (single moment of time) and looked at the height
        of the water along a straight line, we would see peaks and valleys that
        repeat their shape over and over again. This would give us a periodic
        function with an independent variable of position. The period would correspond
        physically to the wavelength, which is the distance at which the shape starts
        to repeat (usually imagined as distance from peak-to-peak).
        </p>

        <p>
        On the other hand, if we had a bobber at a single location and measured its
        height as it bobbed up and down, then we again have a periodic function
        with an independent variable of time. The period now corresponds to a time
        interval over which the pattern of height begins to repeat, which equals the
        time between the bobber reaching its highest point.
        </p>

        <p>
        In reality, physical waves exist in both space and time and should be
        considered as functions of both independent variables. In such a case,
        the physical period is called the wavelength and the temporal (time) period
        is called simply the period. For the purposes of our discussion, we will
        only consider a single independent variable and use the idea of period
        and wavelength interchangeably.
        </p>

        <p>
        The 1963 Nobel prize in Physiology or Medicine was awarded to the
        scientists Alan Hodgkin and Andrew Huxley for their development in 1952 of
        a model of how ion channels in a neuron control the neuron's firing
        patterns. One prediction of their model was that if the stimulus
        on the neuron was sufficiently high then the neuron would fall into
        a steady rhythm of firing or spiking. The resulting graphs illustrate
        a periodic function that is more complex than a simple sine or cosine function.
        The period can be estimated by measuring the interval (spacing) between
        any repeating point on the graph.
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="fig-neuron-spiking">
            <caption>
            Neuron spiking given by the Hodgkin--Huxley model of ion channels.
            </caption>
            <image>
                <description>
                Neuron spiking modeled by the Hodgkin--Huxley model of ion channels.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                \begin{axis}[
                    xmin=0,xmax=100,ymin=-20,ymax=100,
                    ytick={-20,0,...,100},
                    xlabel={time (ms)},
                    ylabel={potential (V)},
                ]
                \addplot[blue] table {data/hodgkin-huxley-data.dat};
                \addplot[black] table {
                    0 0
                    100 0
                };
                \end{axis}
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </figure>

        <p>
        Finding the period from such a graph is challenging because we can only estimate
        the coordinates of the points. Using the actual data as portrayed in a detailed
        table would be better. In the above figure, it looks like over the course of 100 ms
        the pattern repeats almost exactly 7 times. So the period should be close to
        <m>100/7 \approx 14.3</m> ms. The data (table, not shown) suggest that
        the moment when the voltage first crosses <m>V=0</m> occurs at <m>t=1.81</m> ms.
        The voltage crosses this again coming down at <m>t=10.16</m> ms, but the
        moment when the pattern begins again is when it crosses going up at
        <m>t=16.45</m> ms. So our best estimate of the period is <m>p=16.45-1.81=14.64</m> ms.
        </p>

        <p>
        For symmetric waves like the sine and cosine functions, the <term>amplitude</term>
        of the wave describes the height of the wave away from the center, which would
        be the value in the absence of a wave. For this reason, the amplitude of a
        periodic function is usually defined as half the distance between the maximum
        and minimum values. It is harder to justify this definition for examples like
        the Hodgkin<ndash />Huxley spiking model where the center line should be 0 V (neutral)
        so that there is an asymmetry between the distance to maximum and distance to minimum.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection>
        <title>Transformations and Periodic Functions</title>

        <p>
        Suppose we are given data representing some periodic behavior and we want
        to establish a model for those data using a known periodic function.
        It is almost certain that the known periodic function will have the wrong
        amplitude, the wrong period, and the wrong starting point.
        We use the idea of transformations to create a new function that will
        do a better job of representing our data.
        We will use the sine and cosine functions as examples of how this is done.
        </p>

        <p>
        One way to do this is to imagine enclosing exactly one cycle of the
        elementary function in a rectangle and then enclose exactly one cycle
        of the data as the transformed function. The width of each rectangle
        corresponds to the period. The top of the rectangle corresponds to the
        maximum value (peak) and the bottom corresponds to the minimum value (valley).
        Then use the method of function transformation to find the new function.
        </p>

        <example>
            <statement>
             <p>
               Find the formula for the sinusoidal function shown in the following graph.
             </p>

              <image>
                  <description>
                  A sinusoidal graph with a centerline at y=10, a minimum at y=7
                  and maximum at y=13, a period of 8 and maximum at x=1.
                  </description>
                  <latex-image>
                  <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                  <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                  }
                  \begin{tikzpicture}
                  \begin{axis}[
                      xmin=-5,xmax=20,ymin=-3,ymax=18,
                      ytick={0,5,10,15},
                      xlabel={$x$},
                      ylabel={$y$},
                  ]
                  \addplot[blue, samples=100, domain=-1:3]
                      ({1+8*x}, {10+3*cos(deg(2*pi*x))});
                  \addplot[
                      only marks,
                      color=blue
                  ] table {
                      1 13
                      3 10
                      5  7
                      9 13
                  }
                  node [pos=0, above] {$(1,13)$}
                  node [pos=0.33, above right] {$(3,10)$}
                  node [pos=0.66, below] {$(5,7)$}
                  node [pos=1, above] {$(9,13)$}
                  ;
                  \end{axis}
                  \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                  </latex-image>
              </image>
            </statement>
            <solution>
            <p>
            If we know the location of a peak, then the cosine function is a good
            choice for our elementary function because its elementary cycle
            goes from peak to peak. (The sine function has an elementary cycle the
            goes between two consecutive upward crossings of the center line.)
            A single cycle of the cosine function
            is shown in the figure below, along with a single corresponding cycle
            for our transformed data.
            </p>
            <image>
                <description>
                Single cycles of the cosine and of the example
                sinusoidal graph with a centerline at y=10, a minimum at y=7
                and maximum at y=13, a period of 8 and maximum at x=1.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                \begin{axis}[
                    xmin=-5,xmax=20,ymin=-3,ymax=18,
                    ytick={0,5,10,15},
                    xlabel={$x$},
                    ylabel={$y$},
                ]

                \addplot[black, samples=100, domain=-5:20]
                    ({x}, {cos(deg(x))});
                \addplot[
                    only marks,
                    color=black
                ] table {
                    0 1
                    1.57 0
                    3.14  -1
                    6.28 1
                }
                node [pos=0, above left] {$(0,1)$}
                node [pos=0.33, above right] {$(\frac{\pi}{2},0)$}
                node [pos=0.66, below] {$(\pi,-1)$}
                node [pos=1, above right] {$(2\pi,1)$}
                ;
                \addplot[black,dashed] table {
                    0 1
                    6.28 1
                    6.28 -1
                    0 -1
                    0 1
                };

                \addplot[blue, samples=100, domain=-1:3]
                    ({1+8*x}, {10+3*cos(deg(2*pi*x))});
                \addplot[
                    only marks,
                    color=blue
                ] table {
                    1 13
                    3 10
                    5  7
                    9 13
                }
                node [pos=0, above] {$(1,13)$}
                node [pos=0.33, above right] {$(3,10)$}
                node [pos=0.66, below] {$(5,7)$}
                node [pos=1, above] {$(9,13)$}
                ;
                \addplot[blue,dashed] table {
                    1 13
                    9 13
                    9 7
                    1 7
                    1 13
                };
                \end{axis}
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>

            <p>
            If we think of <m>(x,y)</m> based on <m>y=\cos(x)</m> as the
            original elementary function and our transformed relation using <m>(u,v)</m>,
            then we need transformations that accomplish the following mappings:
            <md>
                <mrow> x=0 \: \mapsto \: u=1 </mrow>
                <mrow> x=2\pi \: \mapsto \: u=9 </mrow>
                <mrow> y=-1 \: \mapsto \: v=7 </mrow>
                <mrow> y=0 \: \mapsto \: v=10 </mrow>
                <mrow> y=1 \: \mapsto \: v=13 </mrow>
            </md>
            Notice that <m>\Delta u = 9-1 = 8</m> is the period of the data
            and that <m>\Delta x = 2 \pi - 0 = 2\pi</m> is the natural period
            of the cosine function. Further, notice that <m>\Delta v = 13-7 = 6</m>
            is double the amplitude of our data while <m>\Delta y = 1--1=2</m>
            is double the natural amplitude of the cosine function.
            </p>

            <p>
            Given these observations, we find the actual transformations.
            The horizontal transformation has a slope
            <m>\frac{\Delta u}{\Delta x} = \frac{8}{2\pi}</m>,
            which is exactly the period of the data divided by the natural period
            of the cosine.
            This allows us to write
            <me> u = 1 + \frac{8}{2\pi}(x-0) = 1 + \frac{8}{2\pi} x. </me>
            The vertical transformation has a slope
            <m>\frac{\Delta v}{\Delta y} = \frac{6}{2} = 3</m>,
            which is exactly the amplitude of the data.
            Using the transformation of the centerline <m>y=0</m> to <m>v=10</m>,
            we find that our vertical transformation is given by
            <me> v = 10+3(y-0) = 10 + 3y. </me>
            </p>

            <p>
            To obtain our desired function, we need to rewrite <m>y=\cos(x)</m>
            in terms of <m>(u,v)</m>. Solving for <m>x</m>, we find
            <me> u = 1 + \frac{8}{2\pi} x \quad \Leftrightarrow \quad
            x = \frac{2 \pi}{8}(u-1). </me>
            We now start with <m>v=10+3y</m> to obtain
            <me> v = 10 + 3 \cos(x) = 10 + 3 \cos\left(\frac{2 \pi}{8}(u-1)\right). </me>
            Since we actually wanted our data represented using variables <m>(x,y)</m>,
            we end by making that change:
            <me>
            y = 10 + 3 \cos\left(\frac{2 \pi}{8}(x-1)\right)
            </me>
            </p>
            </solution>
        </example>

        <p>
        The previous example demonstrated how knowing basic information about a
        periodic function allows us to model that function using an elementary
        trigonometric function. In the example, we discovered that the fundamental
        attributes that we needed were the centerline and amplitude (to determine
        the vertical transformation) and the period and a starting point (to
        determine the horizontal transformation). Once these features are
        known, it is straightforward to develop the model.
        </p>

        <theorem>
            <statement>
            Suppose a sinusoidal function has a centerline at <m>y=k</m>
            an amplitude <m>A</m>, a period <m>p</m>, and a maximum occurs at <m>x=h</m>.
            Then one model for the function is given by
            <me> y = k + A \cos\left( \frac{2 \pi}{p}(x-h) \right).</me>
            If instead of a maximum, an upcrossing of the center line occurs at <m>x=h</m>,
            then a model for the function would by given by
            <me> y = k + A \sin\left( \frac{2 \pi}{p}(x-h) \right).</me>
            </statement>
        </theorem>

        <p>
        The reverse process also works. If we start with a formula of a sinusoidal
        function, we can interpret the parameters of the formula to determine
        the period, the amplitude, the center line (vertical shift),
        and the phase shift (horizontal shift).
        </p>

        <example>
            <statement>
            Interpret the formula <m>y=3 \sin(6x+\pi) - 3</m> and use this to sketch
            the graph.
            </statement>
            <solution>
            <p>
            If we thought of <m>y=\sin(x)</m> as the starting point, then this equation
            corresponds to a transformation <m>x=6u+\pi</m> and <m>v=3y-3</m>.
            </p>
            <p>
            To interpret the horizontal transformation, we solve for <m>u</m>:
            <me> u= \frac{1}{6}(x-\pi) = \frac{1}{6} x - \frac{\pi}{6}. </me>
            In words, this says that we multiply all <m>x</m>-coordinates by <m>\frac{1}{6}</m>
            and then shift the graph to the left by <m>-\frac{\pi}{6}</m>.
            Since the original period of sine is <m>2 \pi</m>, the new period
            is <m>p=\frac{1}{6}(2 \pi) = \frac{\pi}{3}</m>.
            The phase shift is the value of the shift <m>-\frac{\pi}{6}</m> and
            gives the <m>x</m>-coordinate of the upcrossing of the sinusoidal graph.
            </p>
            <p>
            To interpret the vertical transformation,
            <me> v=3y-3, </me>
            we see that all <m>y</m>-coordinates are multiplied by 3 and then the
            graph is shifted down by 3. So the amplitude is 3 (from multiplication)
            and the centerline is <m>y=-3</m> (shift).
            </p>
            <p>
            We graph the function by imagining (or physically drawing) the rectangle
            that surrounds a single cycle. We will use <m>(x,y)</m> for our variables,
            where we used <m>(u,v)</m> only to obtain our interpretation.
            The centerline <m>y=-3</m> and amplitude <m>A=3</m> gives us that
            the graph goes from <m>y=-6</m> (minimum) through <m>y=0</m> (maximum).
            The phase shift <m>-\frac{\pi}{6}</m> gives the left edge of the
            initial cycle and the period <m>p=\frac{\pi}{3}</m> gives the width
            of the cycle.
            </p>

            <p>
            Once we have our rectangle, we fill in the sinusoidal graph shape
            to fit in the rectangle. Then we repeat the pattern taking care
            that our period does not change as we draw.
            </p>

            <image>
                <description>
                Graph of y=3sin(6x+pi)-3.
                </description>
                <latex-image>
                <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
                <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
                }
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                \begin{axis}[
                    xmin=-2,xmax=3.5,ymin=-8.2,ymax=2.2,
                    xtick={
                        -1.5708, -1.0472, -0.5236, 0, 0.5236, 1.0472, 1.571,
                        2.0944, 2.6180, 3.1416
                        },
                    xticklabels={
                        $-\frac{\pi}{2}$, $-\frac{\pi}{3}$, $-\frac{\pi}{6}$, 0,
                        $\frac{\pi}{6}$, $\frac{\pi}{3}$, $\frac{\pi}{2}$,
                        $\frac{2\pi}{3}$, $\frac{5\pi}{6}$, $\pi$
                        },
                    ytick={-8,-6,...,2},
                    xlabel={$x$},
                    ylabel={$y$},
                ]

                \addplot[black, samples=100, domain=-2:3.5]
                    ({x}, {3*sin(deg(6*x+pi))-3});
                \addplot[red, thick, samples=30, domain=-0.5236:0.5236]
                    ({x}, {3*sin(deg(6*x+pi))-3});
                \addplot[red,dashed] table {
                    -0.5236 0
                    0.5236 0
                    0.5236 -6
                    -0.5236 -6
                    -0.5236 0
                };
                \end{axis}
                \end{tikzpicture}]]>
                </latex-image>
            </image>
            </solution>
        </example>
    </subsection>

</section>
