<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="power-exponential">
    <title>Power Functions and Exponential Functions</title>

    <!-- Fundamental properties of powers/exponents -->
    <subsection>
        <title>Review Properties of Exponents</title>
        
        <p>
        When we first learned about multiplication, we thought of the process as
        repeatedly adding one of the factors and count with the other factor.
        For example, the numerical expression <m>7 \cdot 4</m> means to add
        four 7's,
        <me>7 \cdot 4 \equiv 7+7+7+7 = 28,</me>
        while the different numerical expression <m>4 \cdot 7</m> means to add
        seven 4's,
        <me>4 \cdot 7 \equiv 4+4+4+4+4+4+4=28.</me>
        The properties of multiplication are consequences of thinking about multiplication
        in such away, such as the commutative property illustrated in this example.
        When dealing with non-integer values, we can't really use the idea of
        repeated addition so different interpretations (e.g., multiplication represents an area)
        are required. But we insist that the rules that we found for integer values
        still need to be true for any number.
        </p>
        
        <p>
        In a similar way, the idea of powers or exponents is based originally on
        the idea of repeated multiplication and then generalized to satisfy basic
        properties. When the power or exponent is a positive integer, we interpret
        this as repeated multiplication with the base multiplied by itself as many
        times as the power indicates:
        <md>
            <mrow> 3^4 = 3 \cdot 3 \cdot 3 \cdot 3 = 81 </mrow>
            <mrow> 4^3 = 4 \cdot 4 \cdot 4 = 64 </mrow>
        </md>
        The properties of exponents can be illustrated using the idea of repeated multiplication.
        </p>
        
        <theorem>
        <statement>
            Let <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> be any numbers and let <m>n</m> and <m>p</m>
            be positive integers. Then exponents defined by repeated multiplication
            satisfy the following properties.
            <md>
                <mrow> a^n \cdot a^p &amp;= a^{n+p} </mrow>
                <mrow> \frac{a^n}{a^p} &amp;= a^{n-p} </mrow>
                <mrow> (ab)^n = a^n \cdot b^n </mrow>
                <mrow> (a^n)^p = a^{n \cdot p} </mrow>
            </md>
        </statement>
        <proof>
        <ul>
            <li> <m>a^n \cdot a^p = a^{n+p}</m>
            <p>
            <m>a^n</m> means multiply <m>n</m> copies of <m>a</m> and <m>a^p</m>
            means multiply <m>p</m> more copies of <m>a</m>. Combined, there are 
            <m>n+p</m> copies of <m>a</m> being multiplied together.
            </p>
            
            <p>Example: <m>a^3 \cdot a^5 = (a \cdot a \cdot a) \cdot (a \cdot a \cdot a \cdot a \cdot a) = a^8</m>
            </p>
            </li>

            <li> <m>\frac{a^n}{a^p} = a^{n-p}</m>
            <p>
            Until we define negative powers, this only makes sense when <m>p \lt n</m>.
            In this case, the division allows <m>p</m> copies of <m>a</m> to cancel in the 
            fraction leaving <m>n-p</m> remaining.
            </p>
            
            <p>Example: <m>{a^5 \cdot a^3} = \frac{a \cdot a \cdot \cancel{a} \cdot \cancel{a} \cdot \cancel{a}}
            {\cancel{a} \cdot \cancel{a} \cdot \cancel{a}} = a^2</m>
            </p>
            </li>

            <li> <m>(ab)^n = a^{n}b^{n}</m>
            <p>
            The definition of <m>(ab)^n</m> is to have a product of <m>n</m> copies of <m>ab</m>.
            By rearranging the factors to group all <m>a</m>'s and <m>b</m>'s together, we
            see there are <m>n</m> copies of each.
            </p>
            
            <p>Example: <m>(ab)^{4} = (ab)\cdot(ab)\cdot (ab)\cdot (ab) 
            = (a \cdot a \cdot a \cdot a) \cdot (b \cdot b \cdot b \cdot b) = a^4 b^4
            </m>
            </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
        </proof>
        </theorem>

        <p>
        In consequence of these properties of exponents when interpreted as repeating 
        multiplication, we will insist on any interpretation as obeying the same rules,
        including negative or non-integer powers. In particular, the rule for division
        gives us an interpretation of negative powers as reciprocals (or multiplicative
        inverses) of the corresponding positive powers.
        </p>
        
        <theorem>
        <statement>
            <p>
            Let <m>a \gt 0</m> and let <m>p</m> be any number, and let <m>n</m> be any positive integer.
            <md>
                <mrow> a^0 = 1</mrow>
                <mrow> a^{-p} = \div a^{p} = \frac{1}{a^p} </mrow>
                <mrow> a^{1/n} = \sqrt[n]{a} </mrow>
            </md>
            </p>
        </statement>
        <proof>
        <ul>
            <li>
            For any non-zero number <m>p</m>, we know 
            <me>a^0=a^{p-p} = \frac{a^p}{a^p} = 1. </me>
            </li>
            
            <li>
            For any number <m>p</m>, since <m>-p = 0-p</m>, we know
            <me>a^{-p} = \frac{a^0}{a^p} = \frac{1}{a^p}. </me>
            </li>
            
            <li>
            For any positive integer <m>n</m>, the mathematical expression
            <m>\sqrt[n]{a}</m> represents the <m>n</m>th root of <m>a</m>,
            which is that number which when raised to the <m>n</m>th power
            equals <m>a</m>. That is exactly what happens to <m>a^{1/n}</m>,
            using the multiplication rule of powers:
            <me>
            (a^{1/n})^n = a^{\frac{1}{n} \cdot n} = a^{1} = a.
            </me>
            </li>
        </ul>
        </proof>
        </theorem>

    </subsection>

    <subsection>
    <title>
    Power Functions and Exponential Functions
    </title>
    
    <p>
    The rules we have discussed for powers provide a constructive way to
    compute powers, first defined for integer powers as repeated multiplication,
    then defined for reciprocals of integers as roots. Combining these two
    methods, computing a power <m>p</m> involving any rational number (ratio of two integers
    <m>k</m> and <m>m \ge 0</m>, <m>p=k/m</m>) as a product power involving roots:
    <me> a^{p/q} = (a^p)^{1/q} = \sqrt[q]{a^p}. </me>
    If we think of this as a function of the base where the power is held
    constant, this defines a family of functions called <term>power functions</term>.
    </p>
    
    <definition>
    <statement>
    An elementary <term>power function</term> is a function where the independent
    variable is raised to a given rational power, <m>p \in \mathbb{Q}</m>.
    <me> \mathrm{pow}_{p}(x) = x^{p} </me>
    A general power function is a constant multiple of an elementary power function,
    <me> f(x) = A x^{p} </me>
    for some constant <m>A</m>.
    </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <example>
        <ol>
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = x^2</m> is an elementary power function with <m>p=2</m>.
        </li>
        
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = \sqrt{8x}</m> is a general power function since we
        can rewrite <m>\sqrt{8x} = \sqrt{8} \sqrt{x} = 2 \sqrt 2 \cdot x^{1/2}</m>.
        Thus <m>f</m> is a constant multiple of the elementary
        power function with <m>p=1/2</m>.
        </li>
        
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = \frac{3}{x}</m> is a general power function since
        <m>\frac{3}{x} = 3\cdot x^{-1}</m> so that we have a constant multiple
        of the elementary power function with <m>p=-1</m>.
        </li>
        
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = x^{\pi}</m> is not technically an elementary power function because the
        power is an irrational number. However, calculus allows us to show that it
        behaves in the same way as a power function in spite of having an irrational
        power.
        </li>
        </ol>
    </example>

    <p>
    On the other hand, it is also possible to consider a function where 
    the independent variable is the power and the base is constant.
    These functions are <term>exponential functions</term>. We do not
    have a constructive way to find these powers for irrational values
    of the independent variable, but calculus (using logarithms) provides a way for us to know
    that the values exist and how to get arbitrarily close to those values.
    </p>
    
    <definition>
    <statement>
    An elementary <term>exponential function</term> is a function where a 
    constant positive base <m>b>0</m> is raised to the power of the independent
    variable.
    <me> \exp_{b}(x) = b^{x} </me>
    A general exponential function is a constant multiple of an elementary exponential function,
    <me> f(x) = A b^{x} </me>
    for some constant <m>A</m>.
    </statement>
    </definition>

    <example>
        <ol>
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = 2^x</m> is the elementary exponential function
        <m>\exp_2(x)</m> with base <m>b=2</m>.
        At integer values of <m>x</m>, this function gives the powers of 2.
        <me>f(0)=2^0=1, \: f(1)=2^1=2, \: f(2)=2^2=4, \: f(3)=2^3=8, \: f(4)=2^4=16 </me>
        </li>
        
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = 3^{2x+1}</m> is a general exponential function, although it does
        not yet look like it because the power is not just the variable <m>x</m>.
        We have to apply the properties of powers to rewrite the formula.
        <me>f(x) = 3^{2x+1} = 3^{2x} \cdot 3^{1} = (3^2)^{x} \cdot 3 = 3 \cdot 9^x</me>
        So <m>f(x)</m> is a general exponential function with base <m>b=9</m>
        and a constant multiple of <m>A=3</m>.
        </li>
        
        <li>
        <m>f(x) = 5^{x^2}</m> is not an exponential function because the
        power is not just the variable <m>x</m> and the rules of powers 
        do not allow it to be rewritten in an exponential form.
        </li>
        </ol>
    </example>

    </subsection>
    
    <subsection>
    <title>Finding Models for Data</title>
    
        <subsubsection>
        <title>Power Function Models</title>
        
        <p>
        A general principle of modeling is that each model parameter typically requires
        one independent equation to specify that value. In the case of a power function,
        <me>y=Ax^p</me>
        there are two model parameters, the scaling multiple <m>A</m> and the power <m>p</m>.
        If the power is known in advance, then you only need one equation and that usually
        comes from a single known data point.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            What is the equation of a quadratic power function passing through
            the point <m>(x,y)=(3,12)</m>?
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Always start with the model equation, which this time involves a power <m>p=2</m>:
            <me>y=Ax^2</me>
            We then create an equation using our data point with <m>x=3</m> and <m>y=12</m>:
            <me>12 = A \cdot 3^2</me>
            If we solve this equation to find <m>A</m>, then we have our model.
            <me>A = \frac{12}{9} \quad \Rightarrow \quad y = \frac{12}{9} x^2</me>
            Note that just finding <m>A</m> did not finish the problem.
            We needed to write down the resulting model for our equation using that value.
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        If we do not know the power in advance, then we need two equations
        which will necessarily come from two different data points. We will use
        logarithms to determine the power. Although the notation below uses the
        common logarithm, in fact the answer is the same regardless of whether 
        you use the common logarithm or the natural logarithm.
        </p>
        
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            What is the equation of a power function passing through
            the points <m>(x,y)=(3,12)</m> and <m>(x,y)=(1,2)</m>?
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Always start with the model equation with unknown model parameters:
            <me>y=Ax^p</me>
            Each data point results in one equation:
            <me> 2 = A \cdot 1^p \qquad 12 = A \cdot 3^p </me>
            Because 1 to any power is 1, the first equation tells us <m>A=2</m>.
            Using the strategy of substitution, we can use this value in the
            other equation to find a second equation,
            <me> 12 = A \cdot 3^p \quad \Rightarrow \quad 12 = 2 \cdot 3^p. </me>
            If we isolate the exponential <m>3^p</m>, then we can use properties of logarithms
            <me> 6 = 3^p \quad \Rightarrow \quad \log(6) = p \log(3) \quad \Rightarrow \quad p = \frac{\log(6)}{\log(3)}. </me>
            The exact model is given by
            <me> y= 2 \cdot x^{(\textstyle \frac{\log(6)}{\log(3)})}. </me>
            Using a calculator, we can approximate <m>p=\frac{\log(6)}{\log(3)} \approx 1.6309</m>
            so that our power function is approximated by
            <me> y \approx 2 \cdot x^{1.6309}.</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        The previous example was kept simple because one data point was at <m>x=1</m>.
        If that data point is not included, then the calculation is a little more complex.
        However, using the log-log transformation means it is really the same as finding
        the equation of a line and apply logarithm rules.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
            What is the equation of a power function passing through
            the points <m>(x,y)=(3,12)</m> and <m>(x,y)=(6,4)</m>?
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Always start with the model equation with unknown model parameters:
            <me>y=Ax^p</me>
            The log-log transformation of data corresponds to computing the logarithm
            of this model and applying properties:
            <me>\log(y)=\log(Ax^p) = \log(A) + p \log(x).</me>
            In other words, if we compute transformed data with <m>u=\log(x)</m> and
            <m>v=\log(y)</m>, then we only need to find the equation of the line
            <me>v = \log(A) + p \cdot u</me>
            and the slope will give us the power and the intercept will be the logarithm
            of the scaling multiple.
            </p>
            
            <p>
            Our two data points become transformed to <m>(u,v) = (\log(3),\log(12))</m>
            and <m>(\log(6), \log(4))</m>. The line has slope
            <me> p = \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta u} = \frac{\log(12)-\log(4)}{\log(3)-\log(6)},</me>
            which we can simplify by using properties of logarithms:
            <me> p = \frac{\log(12/4)}{\log(3/6)} = \frac{\log(3)}{\log(\frac{1}{2})} \approx -1.58496.</me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            To find the intercept (and therefore <m>A</m>), we will continue to use the symbol <m>p</m>
            for the power that we just found since that formula is too complex to repeat many times.
            We use the point-slope form of a line to find an equation
            <me> v-\log(12) = p (u-\log(3)) \quad \Rightarrow \quad v = p \cdot u - p \log(3) + \log(12) </me>
            Again using the properties of logarithms, we can combine the last two terms:
            <me> v = p \cdot u + \log(\frac{12}{3^p}) \quad \Rightarrow \quad A = \frac{12}{3^p}</me>
            This means that our final model (using the original equation)is given by
            <me> y = \frac{12}{3^p} \cdot x^p = 12 \left(\frac{x}{3}\right)^{\log(3)/\log(1/2)} \approx 12 \left(\frac{x}{3}\right)^{-1.58496}.</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        </subsubsection>
        
        <subsection>
        <title>Exponential Models</title>
        
        <p>
        Exponential models have a special property that a linear formula in the power
        can always be rewritten in an exponential form by using properties of powers.
        <me> b^{ax+c} = b^{ax} \cdot b^{c} = (b^a)^{x} \cdot b^{c}</me>
        In this new equation, the value <m>b^a</m> becomes the new base and the constant <m>b^c</m>
        becomes the new scaling multiple.
        Consequently, we have an exponential model if we can make it almost look exponential
        but with a linear formula in the exponent. This is often much easier to accomplish.
        </p>
        
        <example>
        <statement>
        Find an exponential model passing through <m>(x,y)=(0,4)</m> and <m>(x,y)=(3,1)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Start with the model equation:
            <me>y=A b^x</me>
            Use the data points to find equations involving the model parameters <m>A</m> and <m>b</m>.
            <md>
                <mrow>4 &amp;= A b^0 \: \Leftrightarrow \: 4=A\cdot 1 \: \Leftrightarrow \: A=4 </mrow>
                <mrow>1 &amp;= A b^{3} \: \Leftrightarrow \: 1 = 4 b^3 \: \Leftrightarrow \: b^3=\frac{1}{4} 
                 \: \Leftrightarrow \: b=\sqrt[3]{\frac{1}{4}} </mrow> 
            </md>
            Now that we know the model parameters, we can write our model equation:
            <me> y = 4 \cdot \left(\sqrt[3]{\frac{1}{4}}\right)^{x}</me>
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        
        <p>
        The previous example was easy because <m>x=0</m> was given for one of the data points.
        If this is not provided, then the calculation is a little trickier.
        </p>

        <example>
        <statement>
        Find an exponential model passing through <m>(x,y)=(2,4)</m> and <m>(x,y)=(6,12)</m>.
        </statement>
        <solution>
            <p>
            Start with the model equation:
            <me>y=A b^x</me>
            Use the data points to find equations involving the model parameters <m>A</m> and <m>b</m>.
            <me> 4 = A b^2 \qquad 12=A b^6 </me>
            One strategy is to use substitution, solving for <m>A</m> in one of the equations
            and substituting the formula into the other equation:
            <me> 4=Ab^2 \quad \Rightarrow \quad A = \frac{4}{b^2} \qquad \Rightarrow \qquad
            12 = (\frac{4}{b^2}) b^6 </me>
            Simplifying this formula, and solving for <m>b</m> we find:
            <me> 12 = 4b^4 \quad \Rightarrow \quad b^4=3 \quad \Rightarrow \quad b = 3^{1/4} </me>
            We have to back-substitute this value of <m>b</m> to find <m>A</m>:
            <me> A = \frac{4}{b^2} = \frac{4}{(3^{1/4})^2} = \frac{4}{3^{2/4}} </me>
            I could have simplified that last fraction, but I want to leave it alone for comparison below.
            Our final model is given by
            <me> y = \frac{4}{3^{2/4}} (3^{1/4})^x. </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            An alternative method for this problem is to recall that exponential models
            appear linear in a semi-log plot. So we can transform our model using a logarithm:
            <me> y = A b^x \quad \Rightarrow \quad \log(y) = \log(A b^x) = \log(A) + x \log(b). </me>
            That is, the slope is the logarithm of the base and the intercept is the logarithm of
            the scaling multiple. Because the variable <m>x</m> is not in a logarithm, we only 
            transform the coordinates <m>v=\log(y)</m>.
            </p>
            
            <p>
            Our data points become <m>(x,v) = (2, \log(4))</m> and <m>(x,v)=(6,\log(12))</m>.
            The slope of these transformed data is
            <md>
                <mrow> \log(b) = \frac{\Delta v}{\Delta x} &amp;= \frac{\log(12)-\log(4)}{6-2} = \frac{\log(12/4)}{4}  </mrow>
                <mrow> &amp;= \frac{1}{4} \log(3) </mrow>
            </md>
            Consequently, our model equation for <m>(x,v)</m> (using point<ndash />slope) is given by
            <me> v-\log(4) = \frac{1}{4} \log(3) (x-2) = \frac{x-2}{4} \log(3). </me>
            Isolating the <m>v</m> and using properties of logarithms to combine terms, we find
            <me> v= \frac{x-2}{4} \log(3) + \log(4) = \log(3^{(x-2)/4}) + \log(4) = \log(4 \cdot 3^{(x-2)/4}). </me>
            Recalling that <m>v = \log(y)</m> and comparing our formula, we have
            <me> y = 4 \cdot 3^{(x-2)/4} </me>
            </p>
            
            <p>
            The second formula is much cleaner looking because we have expressed our model
            as an exponential involving a convenient linear formula in the exponent.
            Notice that if we were to expand out the terms in the exponent and use properties
            of powers, we actually have the same model in both formulas.
            More significantly, notice that the second formula is a simple transformation
            of the graph <m>y=3^x</m> where the vertical transformation is a scaling by factor 4
            and the horizontal transformation involves a horizontal shift of 2 and another
            scaling by factor 4.
            </p>
        </solution>
        </example>
        </subsection>
    </subsection>
</section>