<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- This file is part of the book                -->
<!--                                              -->
<!--      A Modeling Approach to Calculus         -->
<!--                                              -->
<!-- Copyright (C) 2015  D. Brian Walton          -->
<!-- See the file COPYING for copying conditions. -->
   
<section xml:id="sequences-accumulation">
  <title>Sequences from Accumulation</title>

  <introduction>
    <title>Overview</title>
    
    <p>
    One of the most important mathematical ideas in calculus is 
    that of an accumulation of change for physical quantities. 
    We start by thinking about change and accumulation of change for sequences.
    Eventually, this will lead us to the calculus ideas of the derivative and of definite integrals. 
    </p>
    <p>
    In this section, we learn explore sequences through their differences and accumulations.
    The differences for a sequence defines a new sequence which we call the increments.
    We introduce the mathematical notation for adding the terms of a sequence using summation notation.
    We also learn about conditions which determine when a sequence will be 
    increasing, decreasing, concave up and concave down based on properties of the increments.
    </p>
  </introduction>
  
  <subsection>
    <title>Sequence Differences and Accumulation</title>
    
    <p>
    When we first discussed arithmetic sequences, we learned that they had a constant increment.
    For example, the sequence <m>x=(1, 4, 7, 10, 13, \ldots)</m> has a constant increment of <m>+3</m>.
    Sometimes, more complicated sequences can also be understood which have variable increments.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <p>
      Consider <m>x = (5, 7, 11, 17, 25, \ldots)</m>.
      The increments are not always the same, but we can find a pattern.
      </p>
      <sidebyside width="80%">
        <image>
          <latex-image-code>
          <!-- CDATA prevents certain LaTeX code from being interpreted as xml -->
          <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
          }
          \begin{tikzpicture}[x=2cm]
          \node (x0) at (0,0) {$x_0=5$};
          \node (x1) at (1,0) {$x_1=7$};
          \node (x2) at (2,0) {$x_2=11$};
          \node (x3) at (3,0) {$x_3=17$};
          \node (x4) at (4,0) {$x_4=25$};
          \draw [->] (x0) -- (x1) node[pos=0.5,above] {$+2$};
          \draw [->] (x1) -- (x2) node[pos=0.5,above] {$+4$};
          \draw [->] (x2) -- (x3) node[pos=0.5,above] {$+6$};
          \draw [->] (x3) -- (x4) node[pos=0.5,above] {$+8$};
          \end{tikzpicture}]]>
          </latex-image-code>
        </image>
      </sidebyside>
      <p>
      The increments form a new sequence, which is the sequence of even numbers.
      The next value in the sequence , if the pattern continues, will be <m>x_5=x_4+10=35</m>.
      Our recurrence relation will require a formula involving the index variable.
      Consider the pattern:
      <md>
        <mrow>x_0 &amp;= 5</mrow>
        <mrow>x_1 &amp; = x_0 + 2 = x_0 + 2(1) </mrow>
        <mrow>x_2 &amp; = x_1 + 4 = x_1 + 2(2) </mrow>
        <mrow>x_3 &amp; = x_2 + 6 = x_2 + 2(3) </mrow>
        <mrow>x_4 &amp; = x_3 + 8 = x_3 + 2(4) </mrow>
      </md>
      The pattern can be written 
      as a backward recurrence <me>x_{n} = x_{n-1} + 2n</me> 
      or as a forward recurrence <me>x_{n+1} = x_n + 2(n+1).</me>
      </p>
    </example>
    
    <p>
    The previous example illustrated how we can use the increments of a sequence to describe that sequence.
    We introduce some notation to calculate these increments.
    </p>
    
    <definition xml:id="difference-operators">
      <title>The Backward Difference</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Given a sequence <m>x=(x_n)_{n=n_0}^{\infty}</m> with first index <m>n_0</m>,
        we define the <term>increment sequence</term> or <term>backward difference</term>
        named <m>\nabla x=(\nabla x_n)_{n=n_0+1}^{\infty}</m> defined by
        <me>\nabla x_n = x_n - x_{n-1}.</me>
        We can also define the <term>forward difference</term> <m>\Delta x=(\Delta x_n)_{n=n_0}^{\infty}</m>
        defined by
        <me>\Delta x_n = x_{n+1} - x_{n}.</me>
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <p>
    We will only use the backward difference when discussing increments
    because it is more natural when we work with summation notation.
    Analogous ideas and formulas could be stated for the forward difference but will not be needed.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    For any sequence, we can compute its increments using backward differences.
    In a reverse manner, if we are told the increments and an initial value, 
    we can reproduce the original sequence using a backward recurrence,
    <me>x_n = x_{n-1} + \nabla x_n.</me>
    We call the resulting sequence the accumulation of the increments.
    </p>
    
    <definition xml:id="defn-accumulation-sequence">
      <title>Accumulation Sequence</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Given a sequence of increments, <m>x=(x_n)_{n=n_0}^{\infty}</m>,
        we can define the <term>accumulation sequence</term> <m>u</m>
        using the backward recurrence,
        <me>u_n = u_{n-1} + x_n, \quad n \ge n_0,</me>
        and an initial value.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <p>
    Notice that the first index of the increments will always be one later 
    than the first index of the corresponding accumulation.
    </p>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Find the first six terms of the accumulation sequence named <m>s</m> with
        increments defined by <m>x=(x_n)_{n=-1}^{\infty} = (-3,0,3,6,9,\ldots)</m>
        and whose first value is 12.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        Because accumulation uses a backward recurrence, 
        the first index of <m>s</m> will be <m>n=-2</m>.
        We can compute the values of the accumulation <m>s</m> by 
        successively adding the increments.
        </p>
        <sidebyside margins="auto">
          <tabular>
            <row bottom="major">
              <cell><m>n</m></cell>
              <cell><m>x_n</m></cell>
              <cell><m>s_n</m></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>-2</cell>
              <cell></cell>
              <cell>12</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>-1</cell>
              <cell>-3</cell>
              <cell>9</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>0</cell>
              <cell>9</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>1</cell>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>12</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>2</cell>
              <cell>6</cell>
              <cell>18</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>3</cell>
              <cell>9</cell>
              <cell>27</cell>
            </row>
          </tabular>
        </sidebyside>
      </solution>
    </example>
    
    <p>
    Because we can recreate a sequence using its increments and initial value,
    knowing that information is enough to identify a sequence.
    In particular, if we have two different ways of describing a sequence and
    they both have the same initial value and same increments, then they are the same sequence.
    </p>
    
    <theorem xml:id="thm-sequence-uniqueness">
      <title>Sequences Identified by Increments</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Given any two sequences <m>u</m> and <m>w</m>,
        if <m>u_0=w_0</m> and <m>\nabla u_n = \nabla w_n</m> for all <m>n \gt 0</m>,
        then <m>u_n = w_n</m> for all <m>n \ge 0</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </theorem>
    
    <p>
    We can use this theorem to show that an accumulation sequence has an explicit formula
    by showing that the backward differences of that formula describe the increment sequence.
    </p>
    
    <example xml:id="example-odd-integer-formula">
      <statement>
        <p>
        Show that the sequence of odd integers have explicit formula <m>x_n=2n-1</m>, <m>n=1, 2, 3, \ldots</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        We need to verify the initial value and the increments.
        The first odd integer is 1, which agrees with <m>x_1=2(1)-1 = 1</m>.
        So our explicit formula has the correct initial value.
        Next, we verify the increments.
        Odd integers have increments <m>\nabla x_n = 2</m>, 
        which we verify using the formula.
        <md>
          <mrow>x_n - x_{n-1} &amp; = \big(2n-1\big) - \big(2(n-1)-1\big)</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= 2n-1-(2n-3) = 2n-1-2n+3 </mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= 2 </mrow>
        </md>
        Since <m>x_n</m> has the correct initial value and correct increments,
        <m>x_n=2n-1</m> is the explicit formula for the sequence of odd integers, <m>n \ge 1</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
    
    <example xml:id="example-accumulation-odd-integers">
      <statement>
        <p>
        Using the sequence of odd integers <m>x_n=2n-1</m>, <m>n \ge 1</m>,
        as the increments for an accumulation sequence <m>s</m> with <m>s_0=0</m>,
        show that <m>s_n = n^2</m>.
        That is, show that the accumulation of the odd integers is the sequence of squared integers.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        We start by seeing if the statement makes sense by checking the first few values.
        <md>
          <mrow> x_1 &amp;= 1 </mrow>
          <mrow> x_1 + x_2 &amp;= 1+3 = 4 </mrow>
          <mrow> x_1 + x_2 + x_3 &amp;= 1+3+5 = 9 </mrow>
        </md>
        The pattern appears to hold for the first few values.
        </p>
        <p>
        The initial value using the explicit formula is <m>s_0 = 0^2 = 0</m>,
        the same initial value as stated for the accumulation.
        In order to prove that it will always be true, we need to compare the actual increments.
        The increment of <m>s</m> is computed as the backward difference,
        <md>
          <mrow> \nabla s_n &amp;= s_{n} - s_{n-1} </mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= n^2 - (n-1)^2 </mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= n^2 - (n^2-2n+1) </mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= 2n-1. </mrow>
        </md>
        Because <m>\nabla s_n = x_n</m>, we know that <m>s_n</m> is the accumulation of the odd integers
        with initial value <m>s_0 = 0</m>.
        </p>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  
  <subsection>
    <title>Sequence Behavior</title>
    
    <p>
    Recall that one of the reasons to study sequences was that 
    they could motivate how we think about functions generally.
    The behavior of a sequence, both in terms of monotonicity and concavity,
    can be understood in terms of its increments or differences.
    </p>
    <p>
    First, we look at monotonicity.
    When an increment sequence has positive values, 
    the corresponding accumulation sequence will be increasing. 
    When an increment sequence has negative values, 
    the accumulation sequence will be decreasing. 
    We can extend this idea to an entire range of index values. 
    A sequence is monotone over an index range 
    if it steadily increases or decreases over the entire range.
    </p>
    
    <definition xml:id="defn-sequence-monotonicity">
      <title>Monotonicity of Sequences</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Let <m>u</m> be a sequence and let <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> be valid indexes (integers) 
        with <m>m \lt n</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        We say that <m>u</m> is <term>increasing</term> (order preserving) on the index range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if for every index values <m>i</m> and <m>j</m> with <m>m \le i \lt j \le n</m>, 
        we have <m>u_i \lt u_j</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        We say that <m>u</m> is <term>decreasing</term> (order reversing) on the index range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if for every index values <m>i</m> and <m>j</m> with <m>m \le i \lt j \le n</m>, 
        we have <m>u_i \gt u_j</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <p>
    The monotonicity of an accumulation sequence is completely determined by the sign of the increment sequence. 
    Suppose <m>u</m> is an accumulation of the sequence <m>x</m>.
    Because <m>\nabla u_k = u_k - u_{k-1} = x_k</m>, we know that <m>u_k = u_{k-1} + x_k</m>.
    If <m>x_k \gt 0</m>, then <m>u_k \gt u_{k-1}</m>; 
    if <m>x_k \lt 0</m>, then <m>u_k \lt u_{k-1}</m>.
    This is generalized to an entire range of index values in the following theorem
    by using the transitive property of inequalities.
    </p>
    
    <theorem xml:id="thm-sequence-monotonicity">
      <title>Increment Test for Sequence Monotonicity</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Suppose a sequence <m>u</m> is an accumulation sequence 
        for a particular increment sequence <m>x</m> 
        and <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> are integers with <m>m \lt n</m>
        </p>
        <p>
        The sequence <m>u</m> is increasing on the index range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if and only if the sequence <m>\nabla u_k = x_k \gt 0</m> for every <m>k=m+1,\ldots,n</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        The sequence <m>u</m> is decreasing on the index range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if and only if the sequence <m>\nabla u_k = x_k \lt 0</m> for every <m>k=m+1,\ldots,n</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </theorem>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Consider the sequence <m>x</m> defined explicitly <me>x_k = 2k-13, \quad k=1, 2, 3, \ldots,</me> 
        and the accumulation sequence <m>u</m> defined with <m>x</m> as increments and initial value <m>u_0=10</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        Determine index ranges on which <m>u</m> is increasing and on which <m>u</m> is decreasing. 
        Compute enough values of <m>u</m> to demonstrate these results and create a graph.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        Because <m>u</m> is an accumulation of <m>x</m>, 
        we can determine where <m>u</m> is increasing or decreasing based on the signs of the increments <m>x</m>. 
        We solve the inequality <m>x_k \gt 0</m> using the explicit formula for <m>x_k</m>. 
        <md>
          <mrow> 2k-13 \gt 0 </mrow>
          <mrow> 2k \gt 13 </mrow>
          <mrow> k \gt \frac{13}{2} </mrow>
        </md> 
        The smallest integer greater than <m>\frac{13}{2}</m> is <m>k=7</m>. 
        We see that <m>x_k \gt 0</m> for any <m>k \ge 7</m>. 
        By the same steps, we see that <m>x_k \lt 0</m> for any <m>k \le 6</m>. 
        </p>
        <p>
        By <xref ref="thm-sequence-monotonicity" />, 
        the accumulation sequence <m>u</m> will be increasing on the range <m>6,\ldots,\infty</m> 
        and will be decreasing on the range <m>0,\ldots,6</m>. 
        Notice that the minimum value of the accumulation sequence as at index value <m>n=6</m> 
        where the transition from decreasing to increasing occurs.
        We go back one because increments are the backward difference.
        </p>
        <p>
        We will compute sequence values for <m>n \le 12</m>. 
        First, we compute the values of the increments <m>x</m> using the explicit formula. 
        Once we have the increments, we start with the initial value <m>u_0=10</m> 
        and then repeatedly add one increment at a time to find additional values of <m>u</m>. 
        For conciseness in the table, 
        we will use the common index variable <m>n</m> for both <m>x</m> and <m>u</m>. 
        The value <m>x_0</m>, although potentially defined by the explicit formula, 
        is not used and so is not shown.
        With the sequence computed, a plot of the sequence is shown.
        </p>
        
        <sidebyside>
          <tabular>
            <row>
              <cell> <m>n</m> </cell> 
              <cell> <m>x_n=2n-13</m> </cell> 
              <cell> <m>u_n=u_{n-1}+x_n</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 0 </cell> 
              <cell> n/a </cell> 
              <cell> <m>u_0=10</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 1 </cell> 
              <cell> <m>x_{1}=2(1)-13=-11</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{1}=10+-11=-1</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 2 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{2}=2(2)-13=-9</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{2}=-1+-9=-10</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 3 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{3}=2(3)-13=-7</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{3}=-10+-7=-17</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 4 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{4}=2(4)-13=-5</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{4}=-17+-5=-22</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 5 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{5}=2(5)-13=-3</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{5}=-22+-3=-25</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 6 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{6}=2(6)-13=-1</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{6}=-25+-1=-26</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 7 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{7}=2(7)-13=1</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{7}=-26+1=-25</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 8 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{8}=2(8)-13=3</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{8}=-25+3=-22</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 9 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{9}=2(9)-13=5</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{9}=-22+5=-17</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 10 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{10}=2(10)-13=7</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{10}=-17+7=-10</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 11 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{11}=2(11)-13=9</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{11}=-10+9=-1</m> </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell> 12 </cell>
              <cell> <m>x_{12}=2(12)-13=11</m> </cell>
              <cell> <m>u_{12}=-1+11=10</m> </cell>
            </row>
          </tabular>
        </sidebyside>
        <sidebyside>
          <image>
            <latex-image-code>
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}
              \begin{axis}[
                xlabel=$n$,
                ylabel=$u_n$,
                xtick={0,1,...,12}
              ]
              \addplot[only marks, blue,] coordinates {
                (0,10)
                (1,-1)
                (2,-10)
                (3,-17)
                (4,-22)
                (5,-25)
                (6,-26)
                (7,-25)
                (8,-22)
                (9,-17)
                (10,-10)
                (11,-1)
                (12,10)
              };
              \end{axis}
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
      </solution>
    </example>
    
    <p>
    We now turn our attention to the <term>concavity</term> of the sequence.
    In the previous example, although the accumulation sequence <m>u</m> was first decreasing and then increasing,
    the increment sequence <m>x</m> was increasing over all index values. 
    Indeed, for <m>x_k = 2k-13</m>, we have <m>\nabla x_k = 2 \gt 0</m>.
    The increments started at a negative value and increased steadily, 
    originally become less and less negative and eventually becoming positive. 
    This had the effect of making the graph of the accumulation sequence bend upwards. 
    In this case, the data actually correspond to an upward-opening parabola. 
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The <xref text="title" ref="concavity-average-rates">definition of concavity</xref> 
    for functions was that the slope increased over an interval.
    However, for sequences, the increments are the same as the slopes.
    Consequently, concavity of a sequence is based on whether the increments are increasing or decreasing.
    </p>
    
    <definition xml:id="defn-accumulation-sequence-concavity">
      <title>Concavity of an Accumulation Sequence</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Suppose <m>u</m> is a sequence with increments <m>\nabla u_k = x_k</m> 
        and <m>m</m> and <m>n</m> are index values with <m>m \lt n</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        We say that <m>u</m> is <term>concave up</term> over the range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if the increment sequence <m>x</m> is increasing over the range <m>m,\ldots,n</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        We say that <m>u</m> is <term>concave down</term> over the range <m>m,\ldots,n</m> 
        if the increment sequence <m>x</m> is decreasing over the range <m>m,\ldots,n</m>.
        then 
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <p>
    Because we can test if the increment sequence is increasing or decreasing by looking at its increments,
    the concavity of a sequence is determined from the increments of its increments, 
    which is called the second backward difference.
    </p>
    
    <definition xml:id="defn-second-backward-difference">
      <statement>
        <p>
        Suppose <m>u</m> is a sequence with increments <m>\nabla u_k = x_k</m>.
        The <term>second backward difference</term> of <m>u</m>, written <m>\nabla^2u_k</m>,
        measures the backward difference of the increments,
        <me>\nabla^2 u_k = \nabla x_k = x_k - x_{k-1}</me>.
        The first index of <m>\nabla^2 u_k</m> is two greater than the first index of <m>u</m>.
        (A second forward difference <m>\delta^2 u</m> is defined similarly but will not be used.)
        </p>
      </statement>
    </definition>
    
    <theorem xml:id="thm-sequence-concavity">
      <title>Second Difference Test for Sequence Concavity</title>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Suppose <m>u</m> is a sequence with increments <m>\nabla u_k = x_k</m>.
        If <m>\nabla^2 u_k \gt 0</m> for all <m>k</m> with <m>m \lt k \lt n</m>,
        then <m>x</m> is increasing and <m>u</m> is concave up on the index range <m>m-1,\ldots,n</m>.
        If <m>\nabla^2 u_k \lt 0</m> for all <m>k</m> with <m>m \lt k \lt n</m>,
        then <m>x</m> is decreasing and <m>u</m> is concave down on the index range <m>m-1,\ldots,n</m>.
        If <m>\nabla^2 u_k = 0</m> for all <m>k</m> with <m>m \lt k \lt n</m>,
        then <m>x</m> is constant and <m>u</m> is linear on the index range <m>m-1,\ldots,n</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
    </theorem>
    
    <example>
      <statement>
        <p>
        Determine the monotonicity and concavity of the accumulation sequence <m>u</m> 
        with increments <m>x_k = k^2 -90k + 1600</m>, <m>k=1,2,3,\ldots</m>.
        </p>
      </statement>
      <solution>
        <p>
        For monotonicity, we look at the signs of the increments.
        We find the zeros <m>k^2-90k+1600 = 0</m> and then test the signs in intervals.
        The equation is quadratic, so we can use the quadratic formula.
        <md>
          <mrow>k &amp;= \frac{90 \pm \sqrt{(-90)^2 - 4(1)(1600)}}{2}</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= \frac{90 \pm \sqrt{8100 - 6400}}{2}</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= \frac{90 \pm \sqrt{8100 - 6400}}{2}</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= \frac{90}{2} \pm \frac{\sqrt{1700}}{2}</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;= 45 \pm 5\sqrt{17}</mrow>
        </md>
        In this case, the exact values are not as useful as the approximate decimal values.
        <me>k \approx 24.38 \quad \text{or} \quad k \approx 65.62</me>
        </p>
        <p>
        We need to check values in the intervals.
        <md>
          <mrow> x_0 &amp;= 0^2-90(0)+1600 = 1600 </mrow>
          <mrow> x_{30} &amp;= (30)^2-90(30)+1600 = -200 </mrow>
          <mrow> x_{70} &amp;= (70)^2-90(70)+1600 = 200 </mrow>
        </md>
        This shows that <m>x_k \gt 0</m> for <m>k=1,\ldots,24</m>,
        that <m>x_k \lt 0</m> for <m>k=25,\ldots,65</m>,
        and that <m>x_k \gt 0</m> for <m>k=66,\ldots</m>.
        Consequently, the <em>accumulation sequence</em> is 
        increasing for the range <m>k=0,\ldots,24</m>,
        decreasing for the range <m>k=24,\ldots,65</m>,
        and again increasing for the range <m>k=65,\ldots</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        For concavity, we need to determine where the increment sequence is increasing or decreasing.
        We compute the backward differences of <m>x_k</m> or second backward differences of <m>u</m>.
        <md>
          <mrow>\nabla^2 u_k = \nabla x_k &amp;=x_k - x_{k-1}</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;=\big(k^2-90k+1600\big) - \big((k-1)^2-90(k-1)+1600\big)</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;=k^2-90k+1600 - \big(k^2-2k+1-90k+90+1600\big)</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;=k^2-90k+1600 - k^2 + 92k+1-1691\big)</mrow>
          <mrow> &amp;=2k-91 </mrow>
        </md>
        This equals zero if <m>k=45.5</m>.
        We have <m>\nabla^2 u_k \lt 0</m> for <m>k=2,\ldots,45</m>
        and <m>\nabla^2 u_k \gt 0</m> for <m>46,\ldots</m>.
        Thus, <m>x_k</m> is decreasing and the accumulation <m>u_k</m> is concave down
        on the range <m>k=1,\ldots,45</m>, 
        and <m>x_k</m> is increasing and the accumulation <m>u_k</m> is concave up
        on the range <m>k=45,\ldots</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
        A plot of the sequence with initial value <m>u_0=0</m> is shown below.
        Points within the range where the plot is concave down are colored in blue.
        Points within the range where the plot is concave up are colored in orange.
        The index <m>k=45</m> is included in both ranges and is considered the inflection point.
        </p>
        <sidebyside margins="auto" width="60%">
          <image>
            <latex-image-code>
            <![CDATA[\tikzset{%
            }
            \begin{tikzpicture}
              \begin{axis}[
                xlabel=$k$,
                ylabel=$u_k$,
                scaled y ticks=false,
              ]
              \addplot[samples at={0,1,...,44},only marks, blue, mark size=1pt] 
                { x*(x+1)*(2*x+1)/6 - 90*x*(x+1)/2 + 1600*x };
              \addplot[samples at={45},only marks, black, mark size=1pt] 
                { x*(x+1)*(2*x+1)/6 - 90*x*(x+1)/2 + 1600*x };
              \addplot[samples at={46,47,...,90},only marks, orange, mark size=1pt] 
                { x*(x+1)*(2*x+1)/6 - 90*x*(x+1)/2 + 1600*x };
              \end{axis}
            \end{tikzpicture}]]>
            </latex-image-code>
          </image>
        </sidebyside>
      </solution>
    </example>
  </subsection>
  <subsection>
    <title>Summary</title>
    <p>
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>
        Every sequence <m>x</m> can be interpreted as an accumulation of increments, 
        which we measure using backward differences,
        <me>\nabla x_n = x_n - x_{n-1}</me>.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        Given a sequence <m>x = (x_n)_{n=1}^{\infty}</m>,
        we can define a new sequence <m>u</m> called the <term>accumulation sequence</term> of <m>x</m>
        with a recurrence relation
        <me>u_{n} = u_{n-1} + x_n</me>
        and an initial value <m>u_0</m> 
        so that the increments of <m>u</m> is given by the sequence <m>x</m>, <m>\nabla u_n = x_n</m>.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        If two sequences share the same initial value and the same increments, 
        then the sequences are identical. (See <xref ref="thm-sequence-uniqueness"/>.)
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        The <xref text="title" ref="thm-sequence-monotonicity"/> shows 
        that a sequence is increasing over the range of index values
        for which the increments are positive
        and decreasing over the range of index values
        for which the increments are negative.
        </p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>
        The <xref text="title" ref="thm-sequence-concavity"/> shows 
        that a sequence is concave up over the range of index values
        for which the second backward differences are positive
        and concave down over the range of index values
        for which the second backward differences are negative.
        </p>
      </li>
    </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>
  <exercises>
    <exercisegroup>
      <introduction>
        <p>
        Find the first six terms of the indicated accumulation sequence
        for the given increment sequence.
        Clearly indicate the relevant index values.
        </p>
      </introduction>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          Find <m>u</m> with increments defined by <m>x=(x_k)_{k=2}^\infty = (-4,-2,0,2,4,6,\ldots)</m>
          and initial value <m>21</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          Find <m>w</m> with increments defined by <m>y=(y_i)_{i=0}^\infty = (1,-1,1,1,-1,-1,1,1,1,-1,\ldots)</m>
          and initial value <m>0</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercisegroup>
    <exercisegroup>
      <introduction>
        <p>
        In the following problems, show that explicit definition and recursive definition
        define the same sequence. If not, explain why.
        </p>
      </introduction>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = 3n-5</m> for <m>n=-2, -1, 0, \ldots</m> defines the same sequence as
          <m>x_n = x_{n-1} + 3</m> with <m>x_{-2} = -11</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = 2^{n+1}-1</m> for <m>n=0, 1, 2, \ldots</m> defines the same sequence as
          <m>x_{n} = x_{n-1} + 2^n</m> with <m>x_{0} = 1</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = n^2 - n</m> for <m>n=0, 1, 2, \ldots</m> defines the same sequence as
          <m>x_{n} = x_{n-1} + n</m> with <m>x_{0} = 0</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = \frac{1}{2}(3^n-1)</m> for <m>n=0, 1, 2, \ldots</m> defines the same sequence as
          <m>x_{n+1} = x_{n} + 3^n</m> with <m>x_{0} = 0</m>.
          Note: The recursive formula uses a forward recurrence,
          so either compare forward differences or rewrite the recursive equation as a backward recurrence.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercisegroup>
    <exercisegroup>
      <introduction>
        <p>
        Determine the monotonicity and concavity for each sequence,
        providing the ranges of index values for each behavior.
        </p>
      </introduction>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = 3n-25</m> for <m>n=0,1,\ldots</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = 300-7n</m> for <m>n=0,1,\ldots</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = n^2 - 40n + 90</m> for <m>n=0,1,\ldots</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>x_n = 500 + 75 n - n^2</m> for <m>n=0,1,\ldots</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>\nabla x_n = 4n-70</m> for <m>n=1,2,\ldots</m> with <m>x_0 = 20</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>\nabla x_n = 50-3n</m> for <m>n=1,2,\ldots</m> with <m>x_0 = -10</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>\nabla x_n = n^2 - 30n</m> for <m>n=1,2,\ldots</m> with <m>x_0 = 0</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
      <exercise>
        <statement>
          <p>
          <m>\nabla x_n = -100 + 75n - n^2</m> for <m>n=1,2,\ldots</m> with <m>x_0 = 0</m>.
          </p>
        </statement>
      </exercise>
    </exercisegroup>
  </exercises>
</section>